
<!DOCTYPE html PUBLIC "-//W3C//DTD XHTML 1.0 Transitional//EN"
    "http://www.w3.org/TR/xhtml1/DTD/xhtml1-transitional.dtd">
<html xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml" xml:lang="en" lang="en">
<head>
<link rel="stylesheet" href="babbage.css" type="text/css" />
<title>Sketch of The Analytical Engine</title>
<meta http-equiv="Content-Type" content="text/html; charset=iso-8859-1" />
<meta name="keywords" content="Babbage, Analytical, Engine, Ada, Augusta, Lovelace, Menabrea, Sketch, Bernoulli" />
<meta name="description" content="Sketch of The Analytical Engine" />
<meta name="author" content="L. F. Menabrea and Ada Augusta, Countess of Lovelace" />
<meta name="robots" content="index" />
</head>

<body>
<center>
<h1>Sketch of<br /><img src="figures/aetitlewt.png" width="513" height="51"
    alt="The Analytical Engine" /><br />
Invented by Charles Babbage
</h1>
<h3>
By L. F. MENABREA<br />
<em>of Turin, Officer of the Military Engineers</em>
</h3>

from the <em lang="fr">Biblioth&egrave;que Universelle de Gen&egrave;ve</em>, October, 1842, 
No. 82

<p class="c">
<font size="+1">
With notes upon the Memoir by the Translator<br />
ADA AUGUSTA, COUNTESS OF LOVELACE
</font>
</p>
</center>

<center>
<img src="figures/scrule.png" width="448" height="16" alt="----------------------------------------" />
</center>

<p>

Those labours which belong to the various branches of the mathematical 
sciences, although on first consideration they seem to be the exclusive 
province of intellect, may, nevertheless, be divided into two distinct 
sections; one of which may be called the mechanical, because it is 
subjected to precise and invariable laws, that are capable of being 
expressed by means of the operations of matter; while the other, 
demanding the intervention of reasoning, belongs more specially to the 
domain of the understanding. This admitted, we may propose to execute, 
by means of machinery, the mechanical branch of these labours, reserving 
for pure intellect that which depends on the reasoning faculties. Thus the 
rigid exactness of those laws which regulate numerical calculations must 
frequently have suggested the employment of material instruments, either 
for executing the whole of such calculations or for abridging them; and 
thence have arisen several inventions having this object in view, but which 
have in general but partially attained it. For instance, the much-admired 
<a href="pascal.html">machine of Pascal</a> is now simply an object of curiosity, which, whilst it 
displays the powerful intellect of its inventor, is yet of little utility in itself. 
Its powers extended no further than the execution of the <a name="BKnote1" href="sketch_foot.html#note1">first four</a>
operations of arithmetic, and indeed were in reality confined to that of the 
first two, since multiplication and division were the result of a series of 
additions and subtractions. The chief drawback hitherto on most of such 
machines is, that they require the continual intervention of a human agent 
to regulate their movements, and thence arises a source of errors; so that, 
if their use has not become general for large numerical calculations, it is 
because they have not in fact resolved the double problem which the 
question presents, that of <em>correctness</em> in the results, united with
<em>economy</em> of time.
</p>

<p>

Struck with similar reflections, Mr. Babbage has devoted some years to 
the realization of a gigantic idea. He proposed to himself nothing less than 
the construction of a machine capable of executing not merely 
arithmetical calculations, but even all those of analysis, if their laws are 
known. The imagination is at first astounded at the idea of such an 
undertaking; but the more calm reflection we bestow on it, the less 
impossible does success appear, and it is felt that it may depend on the 
discovery of some principle so general, that, if applied to machinery, the 
latter may be capable of mechanically translating the operations which 
may be indicated to it by algebraical notation. The illustrious inventor 
having been kind enough to communicate to me some of his views on this 
subject during a visit he made at Turin, I have, with his approbation, 
thrown together the impressions they have left on my mind. But the reader 
must not expect to find a description of Mr. Babbage's engine; the 
comprehension of this would entail studies of much length; and I shall 
endeavour merely to give an insight into the end proposed, and to develop 
the principles on which its attainment depends.
</p>

<p>

I must first premise that this engine is entirely different from that of which 
there is a notice in the &lsquo;Treatise on the Economy of Machinery,&rsquo; by the 
same author. But as the latter <a name="BKnote2"  href="sketch_foot.html#note2">gave rise</a> to the idea of
the engine in question, I consider it will be a useful preliminary briefly to 
recall what were Mr. Babbage's first essays, and also the circumstances 
in which they originated.
</p>

<p>

It is well known that the French government, wishing to promote the 
extension of the decimal system, had ordered the construction of 
logarithmical and trigonometrical tables of enormous extent. M. de Prony, 
who had been entrusted with the direction of this undertaking, divided it 
into three sections, to each of which was appointed a special class of 
persons. In the first section the formul&aelig; were so combined as to render 
them subservient to the purposes of numerical calculation; in the second, 
these same formul&aelig; were calculated for values of the variable, selected at 
certain successive distances; and under the third section, comprising 
about eighty individuals, who were most of them only acquainted with the 
first two rules of arithmetic, the values which were intermediate to those 
calculated by the second section were interpolated by means of simple 
additions and subtractions.
</p>

<p>

An undertaking similar to that just mentioned having been entered upon in 
England, Mr. Babbage conceived that the operations performed under the 
third section might be executed by a machine; and this idea he realized by 
means of mechanism, which has been in part put together, and to which 
the name Difference Engine is applicable, on account of the principle 
upon which its construction is founded. To give some notion of this, it will 
suffice to consider the series of whole square numbers, 1, 4, 9, 16, 25, 36, 
49, 64, &amp;c. By subtracting each of these from the succeeding one, we 
obtain a new series, which we will name the Series of First Differences, 
consisting of the numbers 3, 5, 7, 9, 11, 13, 15, &amp;c. On subtracting from 
each of these the preceding one, we obtain the Second Differences, which 
are all constant and equal to 2. We may represent this succession of 
operations, and their results, in the following table.
</p>

<center>
<img src="figures/menat1.png" width="345" height="297"
     alt="Squares, First, and Second Differences" />
</center>

<p>

From the mode in which the last two columns B and C have been formed, 
it is easy to see, that if, for instance, we desire to pass from the number 5 
to the succeeding one 7, we must add to the former the constant difference 
2; similarly, if from the square number 9 we would pass to the following 
one 16, we must add to the former the difference 7, which difference is in 
other words the preceding difference 5, plus the constant difference 2; or 
again, which comes to the same thing, to obtain 16 we have only to add 
together the three numbers 2, 5, 9, placed obliquely in the direction <em>ab</em>. 
Similarly, we obtain the number 25 by summing up the three numbers 
placed in the oblique direction <em>dc</em>: commencing by the addition 2+7, we 
have the first difference 9 consecutively to 7; adding 16 to the 9 we have 
the square 25. We see
then that the three numbers 2, 5, 9 being given, the whole series of 
successive square numbers, and that of their first differences likewise may 
be obtained by means of simple additions.
</p>


<p>

Now, to conceive how these operations may be reproduced by a machine, 
suppose the latter to have three dials, designated as A, B, C, on each of 
which are traced, say a thousand divisions, by way of example, over which 
a needle shall pass. The two dials, C, B, shall have in addition a registering 
hammer, which is to give a number of strokes equal to that of the divisions 
indicated by the needle. For each stroke of the registering hammer of the 
dial C, the needle B shall advance one division; similarly, the needle A 
shall advance one division for every stroke of the registering hammer of 
the dial B. Such is the general disposition of the mechanism.
</p>

<p>

This being understood, let us, at the beginning of the series of operations 
we wish to execute, place the needle C on the division 2, the needle B on 
the division 5, and the needle A on the division 9. Let us allow the hammer 
of the dial C to strike; it will strike twice, and at the same time the needle B 
will pass over two divisions. The latter will then indicate the number 7, 
which succeeds the number 5 in the column of first differences. If we now 
permit the hammer of the dial B to strike in its turn, it will strike seven 
times, during which the needle A will advance seven divisions; these added 
to the nine already marked by it will give the number 16, which is the 
square number consecutive to 9. If we now recommence these operations, 
beginning with the needle C, which is always to be left on the division 2, 
we shall perceive that by repeating them indefinitely, we may successively 
reproduce the series of whole square numbers by means of a very simple 
mechanism.
</p>

<p>

The theorem on which is based the construction of the machine we have 
just been describing, is a particular case of the following more general 
theorem: that if in any polynomial whatever, the highest power of whose 
variable is <em>m</em>, this same variable be increased by equal degrees; the 
corresponding values of the polynomial then calculated, and the first, 
second, third, &amp;c. differences of these be taken (as for the preceding series 
of squares); the <em>m</em>th differences will all be equal to each other. So that, in 
order to reproduce the series of values of the polynomial by means of a 
machine analogous to the one above described, it is sufficient that there be 
(<em>m</em>+1) dials, having the mutual relations we have indicated. As the 
differences may be either positive or negative, the machine will have a 
contrivance for either advancing or retrograding each needle, according as 
the number to be algebraically added may have the sign <em>plus</em> or <em>minus</em>.
</p>

<p>

If from a polynomial we pass to a series having an infinite number of 
terms, arranged according to the ascending powers of the variable, it would 
at first appear, that in order to apply the machine to the calculation of the 
function represented by such a series, the mechanism must include an 
infinite number of dials, which would in fact render the thing impossible. 
But in many cases the difficulty will disappear, if we observe that for a 
great number of functions the series which represent them may be rendered 
convergent; so that, according to the degree of approximation desired, we 
may limit ourselves to the calculation of a certain number of terms of the 
series, neglecting the rest. By this method the question is reduced to the 
primitive case of a finite polynomial. It is thus that we can calculate the 
succession of the logarithms of numbers. But since, in this particular 
instance, the terms which had been originally neglected receive increments 
in a ratio so continually increasing for equal increments of the variable, that 
the degree of approximation required would ultimately be affected, it is 
necessary, at certain intervals, to calculate the value of the function by 
different methods, and then respectively to use the results thus obtained, as 
data whence to deduce, by means of the machine, the other intermediate 
values. We see that the machine here performs the office of the third 
section of calculators mentioned in describing the tables computed by 
order of the French government, and that the end originally proposed is 
thus fulfilled by it.
</p>

<p>

Such is the nature of the first machine which Mr. Babbage conceived. We 
see that its use is confined to cases where the numbers required are such as 
can be obtained by means of simple additions or subtractions; that the 
machine is, so to speak, merely the expression
of <a href="#NoteA">one particular theorem</a> of analysis; and that, in short, its operations 
cannot be extended so as to embrace the solution of an infinity of other 
questions included within the domain of mathematical analysis. It was 
while contemplating the vast field which yet remained to be traversed, that 
Mr. Babbage, renouncing his original essays, conceived the plan of 
another system of mechanism whose operations should themselves possess 
all the generality of algebraical notation, and which, on this account, he 
denominates the <em>Analytical Engine</em>.
</p>

<p>

Having now explained the state of the question, it is time for me to
develop the principle on which is based the construction of this
latter machine.  When analysis is employed for the solution of any
problem, there are usually two classes of operations to execute:
first, the numerical calculation of the various coefficients; and
secondly, their distribution in relation to the quantities affected by
them.  If, for example, we have to obtain the product of two binomials
(<em>a</em>+<em>bx</em>) (<em>m</em>+<em>nx</em>), the result will be
represented by <em>am</em> + (<em>an</em> + <em>bm</em>) <em>x</em> +
<em>bnx</em><sup>2</sup>, in which expression we must first calculate <em>am</em>,
<em>an</em>, <em>bm</em>, <em>bn</em>; then take the sum of
<em>an</em> + <em>bm</em>; and lastly, respectively distribute the
coefficients thus obtained amongst the powers of the variable.  In
order to reproduce these operations by means of a machine, the latter
must therefore possess two distinct sets of powers: first, that of
executing numerical calculations; secondly, that of rightly
distributing the values so obtained.
</p>

<p>

But if human intervention were necessary for directing each of these partial 
operations, nothing would be gained under the heads of correctness and 
economy of time; the machine must therefore have the additional requisite 
of executing by itself all the successive operations required for the solution 
of a problem proposed to it, when once the <em>primitive numerical data</em> for 
this same problem have been introduced.  Therefore, since, from the 
moment that the nature of the calculation to be executed or of the problem 
to be resolved have been indicated to it, the machine is, by its own intrinsic 
power, of itself to go through all the intermediate operations which lead to 
the proposed result, it must exclude all methods of trial and guess-work, 
and can only admit the <a name="BKnote3" href="sketch_foot.html#note3">direct processes of calculation.</a>
</p>

<p>

It is necessarily thus; for the machine is not a thinking being, but simply an 
automaton which acts according to the laws imposed upon it. This being 
fundamental, one of the earliest researches its author had to undertake, was 
that of finding means for effecting the division
of one number by another without using the method of guessing indicated 
by the usual rules of arithmetic. The difficulties of effecting this 
combination were far from being among the least; but upon it depended 
the success of every other. Under the impossibility of my here explaining 
the process through which this end is attained, we must limit ourselves to 
admitting that the first four operations of arithmetic, that is addition, 
subtraction, multiplication and division, can be performed in a direct 
manner through the intervention of the machine. <a name="notes1" class="f">This granted,</a> the machine 
is thence capable of performing every species of numerical calculation, for 
all such calculations ultimately resolve themselves into the four operations 
we have just named. To conceive how the machine can now go through its 
functions according to the laws laid down, we will begin by giving an idea 
of the manner in which it materially represents numbers.
</p>

<p>

Let us conceive a pile or vertical column consisting of an indefinite number 
of circular discs, all pierced through their centres by a common axis, 
around which each of them can take an independent rotatory movement. If 
round the edge of each of these discs are written the ten figures which 
constitute our numerical alphabet, we may then, by arranging a series of 
these figures in the same vertical line, express in this manner any number 
whatever. It is sufficient for this purpose that the first disc represent units, 
the second tens, the third hundreds, and so on. When two numbers have 
been thus written on two distinct columns, we may propose to combine 
them arithmetically with each other, and to obtain the result on a third 
column. In general, if we have a <a href="#NoteB">series of columns</a>
consisting of discs, 
which columns we will designate as V<sub>0</sub>, V<sub>1</sub>, V<sub>2</sub>, V<sub>3</sub>, V<sub>4</sub>, &amp;c., we may 
require, for instance, to divide the number written on the column V<sub>1</sub> by that 
on the column V<sub>4</sub>, and to obtain the result on the column V<sub>7</sub>. To effect this 
operation, we must impart to the machine two distinct arrangements; 
through the first it is prepared for executing <em>a division</em>, and through the 
second the columns it is to operate on are indicated to it, and also the 
column on which the result is to be represented. If this division is to be 
followed, for example, by the addition of two numbers taken on other 
columns, the two original arrangements of the machine must be 
simultaneously altered. If, on the contrary, a series of operations of the 
same nature is to be gone through, then the first of the original 
arrangements will remain, and the second alone must be altered Therefore, 
the arrangements that may be communicated to
the various parts of the machine may be distinguished into two principal 
classes:
</p>

<blockquote>
First, that relative to the <em>Operations</em>.<br />
Secondly, that relative to the <em>Variables</em>.
</blockquote>

<p>
By this latter we mean that which indicates the columns to be operated on. 
As for the operations themselves, they are executed by a special apparatus, 
which is designated by the name of <em>mill</em>, and which itself contains a certain 
number of columns, similar to those of the Variables. When two numbers 
are to be combined together, the machine commences by effacing them 
from the columns where they are written, that is, it
places <a name="BKnote4" href="sketch_foot.html#note4"><em>zero</em></a> on every 
disc of the two vertical lines on which the numbers were represented; and it 
transfers the numbers to the mill. There, the apparatus having been 
disposed suitably for the required operation, this latter is effected, and, 
when completed, the result itself is transferred to the column of Variables 
which shall have been indicated. Thus the mill is that portion of the 
machine which works, and the columns of Variables constitute that where 
the results are represented and arranged. After the preceding explanations, 
we may perceive that all fractional and irrational results will be represented 
in decimal fractions. Supposing each column to have forty discs, this 
extension will be sufficient for all degrees of approximation generally 
required.
</p>

<p>

<a name="menaref1" class="f">It will now be inquired</a> how the machine can of itself, and without having 
recourse to the hand of man, assume the successive dispositions suited to 
the operations. The solution of this problem has been taken from 
<a href="#NoteC">Jacquard's apparatus</a>, used for the manufacture of brocaded stuffs, in the 
following manner:&mdash;
</p>

<p>

Two species of threads are usually distinguished in woven stuffs; one
is the <em>warp</em> or longitudinal thread, the other the
<em>woof</em> or transverse thread, which is conveyed by the
instrument called the shuttle, and which crosses the longitudinal
thread or warp.  When a brocaded stuff is required, it is necessary in
turn to prevent certain threads from crossing the woof, and this
according to a succession which is determined by the nature of the
design that is to be reproduced.  Formerly this process was lengthy
and difficult, and it was requisite that the workman, by attending to
the design which he was to copy, should himself regulate the movements
the threads were to take.  Thence
arose the high price of this description of stuffs, especially if threads of 
various colours entered into the fabric. To simplify this manufacture, 
Jacquard devised the plan of connecting each group of threads that were to 
act together, with a distinct lever belonging exclusively to that group. All 
these levers terminate in rods, which are united together in one bundle, 
having usually the form of a parallelopiped with a rectangular base. The 
rods are cylindrical, and are separated from each other by small intervals. 
The process of raising the threads is thus resolved into that of moving these 
various lever-arms in the requisite order. To effect this, a rectangular sheet 
of pasteboard is taken, somewhat larger in size than a section of the bundle 
of lever-arms. If this sheet be applied to the base of the bundle, and an
advancing motion be then communicated to the pasteboard, this latter will 
move with it all the rods of the bundle, and consequently the threads that 
are connected with each of them. But if the pasteboard, instead of being 
plain, were pierced with holes corresponding to the extremities of the 
levers which meet it, then, since each of the levers would pass through the 
pasteboard during the motion of the latter, they would all remain in their 
places. We thus see that it is easy so to determine the position of the holes 
in the pasteboard, that, at any given moment, there shall be a certain 
number of levers, and consequently of parcels of threads, raised, while the 
rest remain where they were. Supposing this process is successively 
repeated according to a law indicated by the pattern to be executed, we 
perceive that this pattern may be reproduced on the stuff. For this purpose 
we need merely compose a series of cards according to the law required, 
and arrange them in suitable order one after the other; then, by causing 
them to pass over a polygonal beam which is so connected as to turn a new 
face for every stroke of the shuttle, which face shall then be impelled 
parallelly to itself against the bundle of lever-arms, the operation of raising 
the threads will be regularly performed. Thus we see that brocaded tissues 
may be manufactured with a precision and rapidity formerly difficult to 
obtain.
</p>

<p>

<a name="notes2" class="f">Arrangements</a> analogous to those just described have been introduced into 
the Analytical Engine. It contains two principal species of cards: first, 
Operation cards, by means of which the parts of the machine are so 
disposed as to execute any determinate series of operations, such as 
additions, subtractions, multiplications, and divisions; secondly, cards of 
the Variables, which indicate to the machine the columns on which the 
results are to be represented. The cards, when put in motion, successively 
arrange the various portions of the machine according to the nature of the 
processes that are to be effected, and the machine
at the same time executes these processes by means of the various pieces 
of mechanism of which it is constituted.
</p>

<p>

<a name="menaref5" class="f">In order more perfectly</a> to conceive the thing, let us select as an example 
the resolution of two equations of the first degree with two unknown 
quantities. Let the following be the two equations, in which <em>x</em> and <em>y</em> are the 
unknown quantities:&mdash;
</p>


<center>
<img src="figures/menaeq1.png" width="175" height="62"
     alt="\left\{\begin{array}{l} mx+ny=d\\m'x+n'y=d'.\end{array}\right"/>
</center>

<p>

We deduce 
<img src="figures/menaeq2.png" align="middle" width="121" height="37"
     alt="x=\frac{dn'-d'n}{n'm-nm'}" />, and 
for <em>y</em> an 
analogous 
expression. 
Let us continue to represent by V<sub>0</sub>, V<sub>1</sub>,
V<sub>2</sub>, &amp;c.  the different columns which contain the numbers,
and let us suppose that the first eight columns have been chosen for
expressing on them the numbers represented by <em>m</em>, <em>n</em>,
<em>d</em>, <em>m</em>', <em>n</em>', <em>d</em>', <em>n</em> and
<em>n</em>', which implies that V<sub>0</sub>=<em>m</em>,
V<sub>1</sub>=<em>n</em>, V<sub>2</sub>=<em>d</em>,
V<sub>3</sub>=<em>m</em>', V<sub>4</sub>=<em>n</em>',
V<sub>5</sub>=<em>d</em>', V<sub>6</sub>=<em>n</em>,
V<sub>7</sub>=<em>n</em>'.
</p>

<p>

The series of operations commanded by the cards, and the results 
obtained, may be represented in the following table:&mdash;
</p>

<center>
<img src="figures/menat2.png" width="604" height="349" alt="" />
</center>

<p>

Since the cards do nothing but indicate in what manner and on what
columns the machine shall act, it is clear that we must still, in
every particular case, introduce the numerical data for the
calculation.  Thus, in the example we have selected, we must
previously inscribe the numerical values of <em>m</em>, <em>n</em>,
<em>d</em>, <em>m</em>', <em>n</em>', <em>d</em>', in the order and on
the columns indicated, after which the machine when put in action will
give the value of the unknown quantity <em>x</em> for this particular
case.  To obtain the value of <em>y</em>, another series of operations
analogous to the preceding must be performed.  But we see that they
will be only four in number, since the denominator of the expression
for <em>y</em>, excepting the sign, is the same as that for
<em>x</em>, and equal to <em>n</em>'<em>m</em>-<em>nm</em>'.  In the
preceding table it will be remarked that the column for operations
indicates four successive <em>multiplications</em>, two
<em>subtractions</em>, and one <em>division</em>.  Therefore, if
desired, we need only use three operation-cards; to manage which, it
is sufficient to introduce into the machine an apparatus which shall,
after the first multiplication, for instance, retain the card which
relates to this operation, and not allow it to advance so as to be
replaced by another one, until after this same operation shall have
been four times repeated.  In the preceding example we have seen, that
to find the value of <em>x</em> we must begin by writing the
coefficients <em>m</em>, <em>n</em>, <em>d</em>, <em>m</em>',
<em>n</em>', <em>d</em>', upon eight columns, thus repeating
<em>n</em> and <em>n</em>' twice.  According to the same method, if it
were required to calculate <em>y</em> likewise, these coefficients
must be written on twelve different columns.  But it is possible to
simplify this process, and thus to diminish the chances of errors,
which chances are greater, the larger the number of the quantities
that have to be inscribed previous to setting the machine in action.
To understand this simplification, we must remember that every number
written on a column must, in order to be arithmetically combined with
another number, be effaced from the column on which it is, and
transferred to the <em>mill</em>.  Thus, in the example we have
discussed, we will take the two coefficients <em>m</em> and
<em>n</em>', which are each of them to enter into <em>two</em> different
products, that is <em>m</em> into <em>mn</em>' and <em>md</em>',
<em>n</em>' into <em>mn</em>' and <em>n</em>'<em>d</em>.  These
coefficients will be inscribed on the columns V<sub>0</sub> and
V<sub>4</sub>.  If we commence the series of operations by the product
of <em>m</em> into <em>n</em>', these numbers will be effaced from the
columns V<sub>0</sub> and V<sub>4</sub>, that they may be transferred
to the mill, which will multiply them into each other, and will then
command the machine to represent the result, say on the column
V<sub>6</sub>.  But as these numbers are each to be used again in
another operation, they must again be inscribed somewhere; therefore,
while the mill is working out their product, the machine will inscribe
them anew on any two columns that may be indicated to it through the
cards; and as, in the actual case, there is no reason why they should
not resume their former places, we will suppose them again inscribed
on V<sub>0</sub> and V<sub>4</sub>, whence in short they would not
finally disappear, to be reproduced no more, until they should have
gone through all the combinations in which they might have to be used.
</p>

<p>

<a name="menaref3" class="f">We see, then,</a> that the whole assemblage of operations requisite for
resolving the <a href="#NoteD">two above equations</a> of the
first degree may be definitely represented in the following table:&mdash;
</p>

<center>
<table>
<tr>
<td>
<a href="figures/menat3_l.png" class="i">
<!-- ./textogif -dpi 130 menat3 -->
<img src="figures/menat3.png" width="636" height="627" alt="" />
</a>
</td></tr>
<tr>
<td width="637" align="center">
<font size="-1" face="Helvetica">Clicking on the table displays a <a href="figures/menat3_l.png">larger image</a> of it.
Your browser's &ldquo;Back&rdquo; button will return you to this document.</font>
</td></tr>
</table>
</center>

<p>

In order to diminish to the utmost the chances of error in inscribing the 
numerical data of the problem, they are successively placed on one of the 
columns of the mill; then, by means of cards arranged for this purpose, 
these same numbers are caused to arrange themselves on the requisite 
columns, without the operator having to give his attention to it; so that his 
undivided mind may be applied to the simple inscription of these same 
numbers.
</p>

<p>

According to what has now been explained, we see that the collection of 
columns of Variables may be regarded as a <em>store</em> of numbers, accumulated 
there by the mill, and which, obeying the orders transmitted to the machine 
by means of the cards, pass alternately from the mill to the store and from 
the store to the mill, that they may undergo the transformations demanded 
by the nature of the calculation to be performed.
</p>

<p>

<a name="notes4" class="f">Hitherto no mention</a>
has been made of the <em>signs</em> in the
results, and the machine would be far from perfect were it incapable
of expressing and combining amongst each other positive and negative
quantities.  To accomplish this end, there is, above every column,
both of the mill and of the store, a disc, similar to the discs of
which the columns themselves consist.  According as the digit on this
disc is even or uneven, the number inscribed on the corresponding
column below it will be considered as positive or negative.  This
granted, we may, in the following manner, conceive how the signs can
be algebraically combined in the machine.  When a number is to be
transferred from the store to the mill, and <em>vice vers&acirc;</em>, it
will always be transferred with its sign, which will effected by means
of the cards, as has been explained in what precedes.  Let any two
numbers then, on which we are to operate arithmetically, be placed in
the mill with their respective signs.  Suppose that we are first to
add them together; the operation-cards will command the addition: if
the two numbers be of the same sign, one of the two will be entirely
effaced from where it was inscribed, and will go to add itself on the
column which contains the other number; the machine will, during this
operation, be able, by means of a certain apparatus, to prevent any
movement in the disc of signs which belongs to the column on which the
addition is made, and thus the result will remain with the sign which
the two given numbers originally had.  When two numbers have two
different signs, the addition commanded by the card will be changed
into a subtraction through the intervention of mechanisms which are
brought into play by this very difference of sign.  Since the
subtraction can only be effected on the larger of the two numbers, it
must be arranged that the disc of signs of the larger number shall not
move while the smaller of the two numbers is being effaced from its
column and subtracted from the other, whence the result will have the
sign of this latter, just as in fact it ought to be.  The combinations
to which algebraical subtraction give rise, are analogous to the
preceding.  Let us pass on to multiplication.  When two numbers to be
multiplied are of the same sign, the result is positive; if the signs
are different, the product must be negative.  In order that the
machine may act conformably to this law, we have but to conceive that
on the column containing the product of the two given numbers, the
digit which indicates the sign of that product has been formed by the
mutual addition of the two digits that respectively indicated the
signs of the two given numbers; it is then obvious that if the digits
of the signs are both even, or both odd, their sum will be an even
number, and consequently will express a positive number; but that if,
on the contrary, the two digits of the signs are one even and the
other odd, their sum will be an odd number, and will consequently
express a negative number.  In the case of division.  instead of
adding the digits of the discs, they must be subtracted one from the
other, which will produce results analogous to the preceding; that is
to say, that if these figures are both even or both uneven, the
remainder of this subtraction will be even; and it will be uneven in
the contrary case.  When I speak of mutually adding or subtracting the
numbers expressed by the digits of the signs, I merely mean that one
of the sign-discs is made to advance or retrograde a number of
divisions equal to that which is expressed by the digit on the other
sign-disc.  We see, then, from the preceding explanation, that it is
possible mechanically to combine the signs of quantities so as to
obtain results conformable to those <a name="BKnote5" href="sketch_foot.html#note5">indicated
by algebra</a>.
</p>

<p>

The machine is not only capable of executing those numerical calculations 
which depend on a given algebraical formula, but it is also fitted for 
analytical calculations in which there are one or several variables to be 
considered. It must be assumed that the analytical expression to be 
operated on can be developed according to powers of the variable, or 
according to determinate functions of this same variable, such as circular 
functions, for instance; and similarly for the result that is to be attained. If 
we then suppose that above the columns of the store, we have inscribed the 
powers or the functions of the variable, arranged according to whatever is 
the prescribed law of development, the coefficients of these several terms 
may be respectively placed on the corresponding column below each. In 
this manner we shall have a representation of an analytical development; 
and, supposing the position of the several terms composing it to be
invariable, the problem will be reduced to that of calculating their coefficients 
according to the laws demanded by the nature of the question. In order to 
make this more clear, we shall take the following
<a href="#NoteE">very simple example</a>, in 
which we are to multiply (<em>a</em> + <em>bx</em><sup>1</sup>) by (A + B cos<sup>1</sup>&nbsp;<em>x</em>).
We shall begin by 
writing <em>x</em><sup>0</sup> , <em>x</em><sup>1</sup>, cos<sup>0</sup>&nbsp;<em>x</em>,
cos<sup>1</sup>&nbsp;<em>x</em>, above the
columns V<sub>0</sub>, V<sub>1</sub>, V<sub>2</sub>, V<sub>3</sub>; then 
since, from the form of the two functions to be combined, the terms which 
are to compose the products will be of the following nature,
<em>x</em><sup>0</sup>&middot;cos<sup>0</sup>&nbsp;<em>x</em>, 
<em>x</em><sup>0</sup>&middot;cos<sup>1</sup>&nbsp;<em>x</em>,
<em>x</em><sup>1</sup>&middot;cos<sup>0</sup>&nbsp;<em>x</em>,
<em>x</em><sup>1</sup>&middot;cos<sup>1</sup>&nbsp;<em>x</em>,
these will be inscribed above the columns 
V<sub>4</sub>, V<sub>5</sub>, V<sub>6</sub>, V<sub>7</sub>.
The coefficients of <em>x</em><sup>0</sup>, <em>x</em><sup>1</sup>, cos<sup>0</sup>&nbsp;<em>x</em>, cos<sup>1</sup>&nbsp;<em>x</em>
being given, 
they will, by means of the mill, be passed to the
columns V<sub>0</sub>, V<sub>1</sub>, V<sub>2</sub> and V<sub>3</sub>. Such are the primitive data of the problem. 
It is now the business of the machine to work out its solution, that is, to 
find the coefficients which are to be inscribed on V<sub>4</sub>, V<sub>5</sub>, V<sub>6</sub>, V<sub>7</sub>. To 
attain this object, the law of formation of these same coefficients being 
known, the machine will act through the intervention of the cards, in the 
manner indicated by the <a name="menaref4" class="f">following
table:&mdash;</a>
</p>

<map name="menat4" id="menat4">
<area shape="rect" coords="21,61,53,94" href="sketch_foot.html#note5a" alt="Footnote in diagram" />
<area shape="rect" coords="0,0,639,307" href="figures/menat4_l.png" alt="Enlarged image of diagram" />
</map>
<center>
<table>
<tr>
<td>
<a class="i" name="notes5" href="figures/menat4_l.png">
<!-- ./textogif -dpi 115 -colour menat4 -->
<img src="figures/menat4.png" usemap="#menat4" width="639" height="307" alt="" />
</a>
</td></tr>
<tr>
<td width="639">
<font size="-1" face="Helvetica">Clicking on the table displays a larger image of it.
Your browser's &ldquo;Back&rdquo; button will return you to this document.
<a href="sketch_foot.html#note5a">Read footnote</a> in diagram.
</font>
</td></tr>
</table>
</center>

<p>

<a name="menaref2" class="f">It will now be perceived</a> that a general application may be made of the 
principle developed in the preceding example, to every species of process 
which it may be proposed to effect on series submitted to calculation. It is 
sufficient that the law of formation of the coefficients be known, and that 
this law be inscribed on the cards of the machine, which will then of itself 
execute all the calculations requisite for arriving at the proposed result. If, 
for instance, a recurring series were proposed, the law of formation of the 
coefficients being here uniform, the same operations which must be 
performed for one of them will be repeated for all the others; there will 
merely be a change in the locality of the operation, that is, it will be 
performed with different columns. Generally, since every analytical 
expression is susceptible of being expressed in a series ordered according 
to certain functions of the variable, we perceive that the machine will 
include all analytical calculations which can be definitively reduced to the
formation of coefficients according to certain laws, and to the distribution 
of these with respect to the variables.
</p>

<p>

<a name="menaref6" class="f">We may deduce</a> the following important consequence from these 
explanations, viz. that since the cards only indicate the nature of the 
operations to be performed, and the columns of Variables with which they 
are to be executed, these cards will themselves possess all the generality of 
analysis, of which they are in fact merely a translation. We shall now 
further examine some of the difficulties which the machine must surmount, 
if its assimilation to analysis is to be complete. There are certain functions 
which necessarily change in nature when they pass through zero or infinity, 
or whose values cannot be admitted when they pass these limits. When 
such cases present themselves, the machine is able, by means of a bell, to 
give notice that the passage through zero or infinity is taking place, and it 
then stops until the attendant has again set it in action for whatever process 
it may next be desired that it shall perform. If this process has been 
foreseen, then the machine, instead of ringing, will so dispose itself as to 
present the new cards which have relation to the operation that is to 
succeed the passage through zero and infinity. These new cards may 
follow the first, but may only come into play contingently upon one or 
other of the two circumstances just mentioned taking place.
</p>

<p>

Let us consider a term of the form <em>ab<sup>n</sup></em>; since the cards are but a 
translation of the analytical formula, their number in this particular case 
must be the same, whatever be the value of <em>n</em>; that is to say, whatever be 
the number of multiplications required for elevating <em>b</em> to the <em>n</em>th power 
(we are supposing for the moment that <em>n</em> is a whole number). Now, since 
the exponent <em>n</em> indicates that <em>b</em> is to be multiplied <em>n</em> times by itself, and all 
these operations are of the same nature, it will be sufficient to employ one 
single operation-card, viz. that which orders the multiplication.
</p>

<p>

But when <em>n</em> is given for the particular case to be calculated, it will be 
further requisite that the machine limit the number of its multiplications 
according to the given values. The process may be thus arranged. The 
three numbers <em>a</em>, <em>b</em> and <em>n</em> will be written on as many distinct columns of the 
store; we shall designate them V<sub>0</sub>, V<sub>1</sub>, V<sub>2</sub>;
the result <em>ab<sup>n</sup></em> will place itself 
on the column V<sub>3</sub>. When the number <em>n</em> has been introduced into the 
machine, a card will order a certain registering-apparatus to mark (<em>n</em>-1), 
and will at the same time execute the multiplication of <em>b</em> by <em>b</em>. When this is 
completed, it will be found that the registering-apparatus has effaced a 
unit, and that it only marks (<em>n</em>&minus;2); while the machine will now again order 
the number <em>b</em> written on the column V<sub>1</sub> to multiply itself with the product
<em>b<sup>2</sup></em> written on the column V<sub>3</sub>, which will give <em>b<sup>3</sup></em>. Another unit is then 
effaced from the registering-apparatus, and the same processes are 
continually repeated until it only marks zero. Thus the number <em>b<sup>n</sup></em> will be 
found inscribed on V<sub>3</sub>, when the machine, pursuing its course of 
operations, will order the product of <em>b<sup>n</sup></em> by <em>a</em>; and the required calculation 
will have been completed without there being any necessity that the 
number of operation-cards used should vary with the value of <em>n</em>. If <em>n</em> were 
negative, the cards, instead of ordering the multiplication of <em>a</em> by <em>b<sup>n</sup></em>, 
would order its division; this we can easily conceive, since every number, 
being inscribed with its respective sign, is consequently capable of 
reacting on the nature of the operations to be executed. Finally, if <em>n</em> were 
fractional, of the form <em>p</em>/<em>q</em>, an additional column would be used for the 
inscription of <em>q</em>, and the machine would bring into action two sets of 
processes, one for raising <em>b</em> to the power <em>p</em>, the other for extracting the <em>q</em>th 
root of the number so obtained.
</p>

<p>

Again, it may be required, for example, to multiply an expression of the 
form <em>ax<sup>m</sup></em>+<em>bx<sup>n</sup></em>
by another A<em>x<sup>p</sup></em>+B<em>x<sup>q</sup></em>, and then to reduce the product to 
the least number of terms, if any of the indices are equal. The two factors 
being ordered with respect to <em>x</em>, the general result of the multiplication 
would be
A<em>ax</em><sup><em>m</em>+<em>p</em></sup>+A<em>bx</em><sup><em>n</em>+<em>p</em></sup>+B<em>ax</em><sup><em>m</em>+<em>q</em></sup>+B<em>bx</em><sup><em>n</em>+<em>q</em></sup>.
Up to this point the 
process presents no difficulties; but suppose that we have <em>m</em>=<em>p</em> and <em>n</em>=<em>q</em>, 
and that we wish to reduce the two middle terms to a single one 
(A<em>b</em>+B<em>a</em>)<em>x</em><sup><em>m</em>+<em>q</em></sup>.
For this purpose, the cards may order <em>m</em>+<em>q</em> and <em>n</em>+<em>p</em> to be 
transferred into the mill, and there subtracted one from the other; if the 
remainder is nothing, as would be the case on the present hypothesis, the 
mill will order other cards to bring to it the coefficients A<em>b</em> and B<em>a</em>, that it 
may add them together and give them in this state as a coefficient for the 
single term <em>x</em><sup><em>n</em>+<em>p</em></sup>=<em>x</em><sup><em>m</em>+<em>q</em></sup>.
</p>

<p>

This example illustrates how the cards are able to reproduce all the 
operations which intellect performs in order to attain a determinate result, 
if these operations are themselves capable of being precisely defined.
</p>

<p>

Let us now examine the following expression:&mdash;
</p>

<center>
<img src="figures/menaeq3.png" width="351" height="42"
     alt="2\cdot\frac{2^2\cdot 4^2\cdot 6^2\cdot 8^2\cdot 10^2\ldots (2n)^2}{1^2\cdot 3^2\cdot 5^2\cdot 7^2\cdot 9^2\ldots (2n-1)^2\cdot (2n+1)^2}" />
</center>

<p>

which we know becomes equal to the ratio of the circumference to the 
diameter, when <em>n</em> is infinite. We may require the machine not only to 
perform the calculation of this fractional expression, but further to give 
indication as soon as the value becomes identical with that of the ratio of 
the circumference to the diameter when <em>n</em> is infinite, a case in which the 
computation would be impossible. Observe that
we should thus require of the machine to interpret a result not of itself 
evident, and that this is not amongst its attributes, since it is no thinking 
being. Nevertheless, when the cos of <em>n</em>=1/0 has been foreseen, a card may 
immediately order the substitution of the value of &pi;
(&pi; being the ratio of 
the circumference to the diameter), without going through the series of 
calculations indicated. This would merely require that the machine contain 
a special card, whose office it should be to place the number &pi; in a direct 
and independent manner on the column indicated to it.
<a name="notes3" class="f">And here</a> we should 
introduce the mention of a third species of cards, which may be called 
<em>cards of numbers</em>. There are certain numbers, such as those expressing the 
ratio of the circumference to the diameter, the Numbers of Bernoulli, &amp;c., 
which frequently present themselves in calculations. To avoid the necessity 
for computing them every time they have to be used, certain cards may be 
combined specially in order to give these numbers ready made into the 
mill, whence they afterwards go and place themselves on those columns of 
the store that are destined for them. Through this means the machine will 
be susceptible of those simplifications afforded by the use of numerical 
tables. It would be equally possible to introduce, by means of these cards, 
the logarithms of numbers; but perhaps it might not be in this case either 
the shortest or the most appropriate method; for the machine might be able 
to perform the same calculations by other more expeditious combinations, 
founded on the rapidity with which it executes the first four operations of 
arithmetic. To give an idea of this rapidity, we need only mention that Mr. 
Babbage believes he can, by his engine, form the product of two numbers, 
each containing twenty figures, in <em>three minutes</em>.
</p>

<p>

Perhaps the immense number of cards required for the solution of any
rather complicated problem may appear to be an obstacle; but this does
not seem to be the case.  There is no limit to the number of cards
that can be used.  Certain stuffs require for their fabrication not
less than <em>twenty thousand</em> cards, and we may unquestionably far exceed
<a href="#NoteF">even this quantity</a>.
</p>

<p>

Resuming what we have explained concerning the Analytical Engine, we 
may conclude that it is based on two principles: the first consisting in the 
fact that every arithmetical calculation ultimately depends on four 
principal operations&mdash;addition, subtraction, multiplication, and division; 
the second, in the possibility of reducing every analytical calculation to 
that of the coefficients for the several terms of a series. If this last
principle be true, all the operations of analysis come within the domain of 
the engine. To take another point of view: the
use of the cards offers a generality equal to that of algebraical formul&aelig;, 
since such a formula simply indicates the nature and order of the 
operations requisite for arriving at a certain definite result, and similarly 
the cards merely command the engine to perform these same operations; 
but in order that the mechanisms may be able to act to any purpose, the 
numerical data of the problem must in every particular case be introduced. 
Thus the same series of cards will serve for all questions whose sameness 
of nature is such as to require nothing altered excepting the numerical data. 
In this light the cards are merely a translation of algebraical formul&aelig;, or, 
to express it better, another form of analytical notation.
</p>

<p>

Since the engine has a mode of acting peculiar to itself, it will in every 
particular case be necessary to arrange the series of calculations 
conformably to the means which the machine possesses; for such or such a 
process which might be very easy for a calculator may be long and 
complicated for the engine, and <em>vice vers&acirc;</em>.
</p>

<p>

Considered under the most general point of view, the essential object
of the machine being to calculate, according to the laws dictated to
it, the values of numerical coefficients which it is then to
distribute appropriately on the columns which represent the variables,
it follows that the interpretation of formul&aelig; and of results is
beyond its province, unless indeed this very interpretation be itself
susceptible of expression by means of the symbols which the machine
employs.  Thus, although it is not itself the being that reflects, it
may yet be considered as the being which executes the
<a href="#NoteG">conceptions of intelligence</a>.  The cards
receive the impress of these conceptions, and transmit to the various
trains of mechanism composing the engine the orders necessary for
their action.  When once the engine shall have been constructed, the
difficulty will be reduced to the making out of the cards; but as
these are merely the translation of algebraical formul&aelig;, it will, by
means of some simple notations, be easy to consign the execution of
them to a workman.  Thus the whole intellectual labour will be limited
to the preparation of the formul&aelig;, which must be adapted for
calculation by the engine.
</p>

<p>

Now, admitting that such an engine can be constructed, it may be inquired: 
what will be its utility? To recapitulate; it will afford the following 
advantages:&mdash;First, rigid accuracy. We know that numerical 
calculations are generally the stumbling-block to the solution of problems, 
since errors easily creep into them, and it is by no means always easy to 
detect these errors. Now the engine, by the very nature of its mode of 
acting, which requires no human intervention during the course of its 
operations, presents every species of security under the head of
correctness: besides, it carries with it its own check; for at the end of every 
operation it prints off, not only the results, but likewise the numerical data 
of the question; so that it is easy to verify whether the question has been 
correctly proposed. Secondly, economy of time: to convince ourselves of 
this, we need only recollect that the multiplication of two numbers, 
consisting each of twenty figures, requires at the very utmost three minutes. 
Likewise, when a long series of identical computations is to be performed, 
such as those required for the formation of numerical tables, the machine 
can be brought into play so as to give several results at the same time, 
which will greatly abridge the whole amount of the processes. Thirdly, 
economy of intelligence: a simple arithmetical computation requires to be 
performed by a person possessing some capacity; and when we pass to 
more complicated calculations, and wish to use algebraical formul&aelig; in 
particular cases, knowledge must be possessed which presupposes 
preliminary mathematical studies of some extent. Now the engine, from its 
capability of performing by itself all these purely material operations, 
spares intellectual labour, which may be more profitably employed. Thus 
the engine may be considered as a real manufactory of figures, which will 
lend its aid to those many useful sciences and arts that depend on numbers. 
Again, who can foresee the consequences of such an invention? In truth, 
how many precious observations remain practically barren for the progress 
of the sciences, because there are not powers sufficient for computing the 
results! And what discouragement does the perspective of a long and arid 
computation cast into the mind of a man of genius, who demands time 
exclusively for meditation, and who beholds it snatched from him by the 
material routine of operations! Yet it is by the laborious route of analysis 
that he must reach truth; but he cannot pursue this unless guided by numbers;
for without numbers it is not given us to raise the veil which 
envelopes the mysteries of nature. Thus the idea of constructing an 
apparatus capable of aiding human weakness in such researches, is a 
conception which, being realized, would mark a glorious epoch in the 
history of the sciences. The plans have been arranged for all the various 
parts, and for all the wheel-work, which compose this immense apparatus, 
and their action studied; but these have not yet been fully combined 
together in <a name="BKnote6" href="sketch_foot.html#note6">the drawings</a> and
<a name="BKnote7" href="sketch_foot.html#note7">mechanical notation</a>. The
confidence which the genius of Mr. Babbage must inspire, affords 
legitimate ground for hope that this enterprise will be crowned with 
success; and while we render homage to the intelligence which directs it, 
let us breathe aspirations for the accomplishment of such an undertaking.
</p>

<table style="margin-left: 8px;" align="right">
<tr>
<td><img src="figures/adaphotoc.jpg" width="250" height="396" alt="Portrait of Ada Augusta, Countess of Lovelace" />
</td></tr>
<tr>
<td align="center"><font size="-1"><em>Ada Augusta,<br />Countess of Lovelace</em></font>
</td></tr>
</table>


<center>
<h2>NOTES BY THE TRANSLATOR</h2>
<h3><em><a name="NoteA" class="f">Note A</a></em></h3>
</center>

<p>
The particular function whose integral the Difference Engine was 
constructed to tabulate, is
</p>

<center>
<img src="figures/adaeq1.png" width="98" height="24" alt="\Delta^7u_x=0" />
</center>

<p>

The purpose which that engine has been specially intended and adapted to 
fulfil, is the computation of nautical and astronomical tables. The integral 
of
</p>

<center>
<img src="figures/adaeq1a.png" width="92" height="24" alt="\Delta^7u_x=0" />
</center>

<table width="70%">
<tr>
<td align="right" width="1%">being</td>
<td align="center" width="99%"><em>u<sub>z</sub></em> = <em>a</em>+<em>bx</em>+<em>cx</em><sup>2</sup>+<em>dx</em><sup>3</sup>+<em>ex</em><sup>4</sup>+<em>fx</em><sup>5</sup>+<em>gx</em><sup>6</sup>,</td>
</tr>
</table>
<p>

the constants <em>a</em>, <em>b</em>, <em>c</em>, &amp;c.  are represented
on the seven columns of discs, of which the engine consists.  It can
therefore tabulate <em>accurately</em> and to an <em>unlimited
extent</em>, all series whose general term is comprised in the above
formula; and it can also tabulate <em>approximatively</em> between
<em>intervals of greater or less extent</em>, all other series which
are capable of tabulation by the Method of Differences.
<br clear="right" />
</p>

<p>

The Analytical Engine, on the contrary, is not merely adapted for 
<em>tabulating</em> the results of one particular function and of no other, but for 
<em>developing and tabulating</em> any function whatever. In fact the engine may 
be described as being the material expression of any indefinite function of 
any degree of generality and complexity, such as for instance,
</p>

<center>
F(<em>x</em>, <em>y</em>, <em>z</em>, log <em>x</em>, sin <em>y</em>, <em>x<sup>&nbsp;p</sup></em>, &amp;c.),
</center>

<p>

which is, it will be observed, a function of all other possible functions of 
any number of quantities.
</p>

<p>

In this, which we may call the <em>neutral</em> or <em>zero</em> state of the engine, it is 
ready to receive at any moment, by means of cards constituting a portion 
of its mechanism (and applied on the principle of those used
in the Jacquard-loom), the impress of whatever <em>special</em> function we may 
desire to develope or to tabulate. These cards contain within themselves 
(in a manner <a href="#menaref1">explained in the Memoir itself</a>) the law of 
development of the particular function that may be under consideration, 
and they compel the mechanism to act accordingly in a certain 
corresponding order. One of the simplest cases would be for example, to 
suppose that
</p>


<center>
F(<em>x</em>, <em>y</em>, <em>z</em>, &amp;c. &amp;c.)
</center>

<p>

is the particular function
</p>

<center>
<img src="figures/adaeq2.png" width="93" height="20" alt="\Delta^nu_z=0" />
</center>

<p>

which the Difference Engine tabulates for values of <em>n</em> only up to 7. In this 
case the cards would order the mechanism to go through that succession of 
operations which would tabulate
</p>

<center>
<em>u<sub>z</sub></em> = <em>a</em> + <em>bx</em> + <em>cx</em><sup>2</sup> + &middot;&middot;&middot; + <em>mx</em><sup>n&minus;1</sup>
</center>

<p>

where <em>n</em> might be any number whatever.
</p>

<p>

These cards, however, have nothing to do with the regulation of the 
particular <em>numerical</em> data. They merely determine the
<a name="BKnote10" href="sketch_foot.html#note10"><em>operations</em></a> to be 
effected, which operations may of course be performed on an infinite 
variety of particular numerical values, and do not bring out any definite 
numerical results unless the numerical data of the problem have been 
impressed on the requisite portions of the train of mechanism. In the 
above example, the first essential step towards an arithmetical result would 
be the substitution of specific numbers for <em>n</em>, and for the other primitive 
quantities which enter into the function.
</p>

<p>

Again, let us suppose that for F we put two complete equations of the 
fourth degree between <em>x</em> and <em>y</em>. We must then express on the cards the law 
of elimination for such equations. The engine would follow out those laws, 
and would ultimately give the equation of one variable which results from 
such elimination. Various <em>modes</em> of elimination might be selected; and of 
course the cards must be made out accordingly. The following is one mode 
that might be adopted. The engine is able to multiply together any two 
functions of the form
</p>

<center>
<em>a</em> + <em>bx</em> + <em>cx</em><sup>2</sup> + &middot;&middot;&middot; + <em>px</em><sup>n</sup>.
</center>

<p>

This granted, the two equations may be arranged according to the powers 
of <em>y</em>, and the coefficients of the powers of <em>y</em> may be arranged
according to powers of <em>x</em>. The elimination of <em>y</em> will result from the 
successive multiplications and subtractions of several such functions. In 
this, and in all other instances, as was explained above, the particular 
<em>numerical</em> data and the <em>numerical</em> results are determined by means and by 
portions of the mechanism which act quite independently of those that 
regulate the <em>operations</em>.
</p>

<p>

In studying the action of the Analytical Engine, we find that the peculiar 
and independent nature of the considerations which in all mathematical 
analysis belong to <em>operations</em>, as distinguished from <em>the objects operated 
upon</em> and from the <em>results</em> of the operations performed upon those objects, 
is very strikingly defined and separated.
</p>

<p>

It is well to draw attention to this point, not only because its full 
appreciation is essential to the attainment of any very just and adequate 
general comprehension of the powers and mode of action of the Analytical 
Engine, but also because it is one which is perhaps too little kept in view in 
the study of mathematical science in general. It is, however, impossible to 
confound it with other considerations, either when we trace the manner in 
which that engine attains its results, or when we prepare the data for its 
attainment of those results. It were much to be desired, that when 
mathematical processes pass through the human brain instead of through 
the medium of inanimate mechanism, it were equally a necessity of things 
that the reasonings connected with <em>operations</em> should hold the same just 
place as a clear and well-defined branch of the subject of analysis, a 
fundamental but yet independent ingredient in the science, which they must 
do in studying the engine. The confusion, the difficulties, the 
contradictions which, in consequence of a want of accurate distinctions in 
this particular, have up to even a recent period encumbered mathematics in 
all those branches involving the consideration of negative and impossible 
quantities, will at once occur to the reader who is at all versed in this 
science, and would alone suffice to justify dwelling somewhat on the point, 
in connexion with any subject so peculiarly fitted to give forcible 
illustration of it as the Analytical Engine. It may be desirable to explain, 
that by the word <em>operation</em>, we mean <em>any process which alters the mutual 
relation of two or more things</em>, be this relation of what kind it may. This is 
the most general definition, and would include all subjects in the universe. 
In abstract mathematics, of course operations alter those particular 
relations which are involved in the considerations of number and space, 
and the <em>results</em> of operations are those peculiar results which correspond to 
the nature of the subjects of operation. But the science of operations, as 
derived from mathematics more especially, is a science of itself, and has its 
own abstract truth and
value; just as logic has its own peculiar truth and value, independently of 
the subjects to which we may apply its reasonings and processes. Those 
who are accustomed to some of the more modern views of the above 
subject, will know that a few fundamental relations being true, certain other 
combinations of relations must of necessity follow; combinations unlimited 
in variety and extent if the deductions from the primary relations be carried 
on far enough. They will also be aware that one main reason why the 
separate nature of the science of operations has been little felt, and in 
general little dwelt on, is the <em>shifting</em> meaning of many of the symbols used 
in mathematical notation. First, the symbols of <em>operation</em> are frequently <em>also</em>
the symbols of the <em>results</em> of operations. We may say that these symbols are 
apt to have both a <em>retrospective</em> and a <em>prospective</em> signification. They may 
signify either relations that are the consequences of a series of processes 
already performed, or relations that are yet to be effected through certain 
processes. Secondly, figures, the symbols of <em>numerical magnitude</em>, are 
frequently <em>also</em> the symbols of <em>operations</em>, as when they are the indices of 
powers. Wherever terms have a shifting meaning, independent sets of 
considerations are liable to become complicated together, and reasonings 
and results are frequently falsified. Now in the Analytical Engine, the 
operations which come under the first of the above heads are ordered and 
combined by means of a notation and of a train of mechanism which belong 
exclusively to themselves; and with respect to the second head, whenever 
numbers meaning <em>operations</em> and not <em>quantities</em> (such as the indices of 
powers) are inscribed on any column or set of columns, those columns 
immediately act in a wholly separate and independent manner, becoming 
connected with the <em>operating mechanism</em> exclusively, and re-acting upon 
this. They never come into combination with numbers upon any other 
columns meaning <em>quantities</em>; though, of course, if there are numbers 
meaning <em>operations</em> upon <em>n</em> columns, these may <em>combine amongst each 
other</em>, and will often be required to do so, just as numbers meaning 
<em>quantities</em> combine with each other in any variety. It might have been 
arranged that all numbers meaning <em>operations</em> should have appeared on 
some separate portion of the engine from that which presents numerical 
<em>quantities</em>; but the present mode is in some cases more simple, and offers in 
reality quite as much distinctness when understood.
</p>

<p>

The operating mechanism can even be thrown into action independently of 
any object to operate upon (although of course no <em>result</em> could then be 
developed). Again, it might act upon other things besides <em>number</em>, were 
objects found whose mutual fundamental relations could be expressed by 
those of the abstract science of operations, and
which should be also susceptible of adaptations to the action of the 
operating notation and mechanism of the engine. Supposing, for instance, 
that the fundamental relations of pitched sounds in the science of harmony 
and of musical composition were susceptible of such expression and 
adaptations, the engine might compose elaborate and scientific pieces of 
music of any degree of complexity or extent.
</p>

<p>

The Analytical Engine is an <em>embodying of the science of operations</em>, 
constructed with peculiar reference to abstract number as the subject of 
those operations. The Difference Engine is the embodying of <em>one particular 
and very limited set of operations</em>, which (see the notation used in <a href="#NoteB">Note B</a>) 
may be expressed thus (+, +, +, +, +, +), or thus, 6(+). Six repetitions of the 
one operation, +, is, in fact, the whole sum and object of that engine. It has 
seven columns, and a number on any column can add itself to a number on 
the next column to its <em>right-hand</em>. So that, beginning with the column 
furthest to the left, six additions can be effected, and the result appears on 
the seventh column, which is the last on the right-hand. The <em>operating</em>
mechanism of this engine acts in as separate and independent a manner as 
that of the Analytical Engine; but being susceptible of only one unvarying 
and restricted combination, it has little force or interest in illustration of the 
distinct nature of the <em>science of operations</em>. The importance of regarding 
the Analytical Engine under this point of view will, we think, become more 
and more obvious as the reader proceeds with M. Menabrea's clear and 
masterly article. The calculus of operations is likewise in itself a topic of so 
much interest, and has of late years been so much more written on and 
thought on than formerly, that any bearing which that engine, from its mode 
of constitution, may possess upon the illustration of this branch of 
mathematical science should not be overlooked. Whether the inventor of 
this engine had any such views in his mind while working out the invention, 
or whether he may subsequently ever have regarded it under this phase, we 
do not know; but it is one that forcibly occurred to ourselves on becoming 
acquainted with the means through which analytical combinations are 
actually attained by the mechanism. We cannot forbear suggesting one 
practical result which it appears to us must be greatly facilitated by the 
independent manner in which the engine orders and combines its 
<em>operations</em>: we allude to the attainment of those combinations into which 
<em>imaginary quantities</em> enter. This is a branch of its processes into which we 
have not had the opportunity of inquiring, and our conjecture therefore as 
to the principle on which we conceive the accomplishment of such results 
may have been made to depend, is very probably not in accordance with the 
fact, and less subservient for
the purpose than some other principles, or at least requiring the 
cooperation of others. It seems to us obvious, however, that where 
operations are so independent in their mode of acting, it must be easy, by 
means of a few simple provisions, and additions in arranging the 
mechanism, to bring out a <em>double</em> set of <em>results</em>, viz.&mdash;1st, the <em>numerical 
magnitudes</em> which are the results of operations performed on <em>numerical 
data</em>. (These results are the <em>primary</em> object of the engine.) 2ndly, the 
<em>symbolical results</em> to be attached to those numerical results, which 
symbolical results are not less the necessary and logical consequences of 
operations performed upon <em>symbolical data</em>, than are numerical results 
when the data are <a name="BKnote11" href="sketch_foot.html#note11">numerical</a>.
</p>

<p>

If we compare together the powers and the principles of construction of 
the Difference and of the Analytical Engines, we shall perceive that the 
capabilities of the latter are immeasurably more extensive than those of the 
former, and that they in fact hold to each other the same relationship as 
that of analysis to arithmetic. The Difference Engine can effect but one 
particular series of operations, viz. that required for tabulating the integral 
of the special function
</p>

<center>
<img src="figures/adaeq3.png" width="99" height="21" alt="\Delta^nu_z=0;" />
</center>

<p>

and as it can only do this for values of <em>n</em> <a name="BKnote12" href="sketch_foot.html#note12">up to 7</a>, it cannot be
considered as being the most <em>general</em> expression even of <em>one particular</em>
function, much less as being the expression of any and all possible
functions of all degrees of generality. The Difference Engine can in
reality (as has been already partly explained) do nothing but <em>add</em>;
and any other processes, not excepting those of simple subtraction,
multiplication and division, can be performed by it only just to that
extent in which it is possible, by judicious mathematical arrangement
and artifices, to reduce them to a <em>series of additions</em>. The method of
differences is, in fact, a method of additions; and as it includes within its 
means a larger number of results attainable by <em>addition</em> simply, than any 
other mathematical principle, it was very appropriately selected as the 
basis on which to construct <em>an Adding Machine</em>, so as to give to the powers 
of such a machine the widest possible range. The Analytical Engine, on the 
contrary, can either add, subtract, multiply or divide with equal facility; 
and performs each of these four operations in a direct manner, without the 
aid of any of the other three. This one fact implies everything; and it is 
scarcely necessary to point out, for instance, that while the Difference 
Engine can merely <em>tabulate</em>, and is incapable of <em>developing</em>, the Analytical 
Engine can either <em>tabulate or develope</em>.
</p>

<p>

The former engine is in its nature strictly <em>arithmetical</em>, and the results it 
can arrive at lie within a very clearly defined and restricted range, while 
there is no finite line of demarcation which limits the powers of the 
Analytical Engine. These powers are co-extensive with our knowledge of 
the laws of analysis itself, and need be bounded only by our acquaintance 
with the latter. Indeed we may consider the engine as the <em>material and 
mechanical representative</em> of analysis, and that our actual working powers 
in this department of human study will be enabled more effectually than 
heretofore to keep pace with our theoretical knowledge of its principles 
and laws, through the complete control which the engine gives us over the 
<em>executive manipulation</em> of algebraical and numerical symbols.
</p>

<p>

Those who view mathematical science, not merely as a vast body of 
abstract and immutable truths, whose intrinsic beauty, symmetry and 
logical completeness, when regarded in their connexion together as a 
whole, entitle them to a prominent place in the interest of all profound and 
logical minds, but as possessing a yet deeper interest for the human race, 
when it is remembered that this science constitutes the language through 
which alone we can adequately express the great facts of the natural world, 
and those unceasing changes of mutual relationship which, visibly or 
invisibly, consciously or unconsciously to our immediate physical 
perceptions, are interminably going on in the agencies of the creation we 
live amidst: those who thus think on mathematical truth as the instrument 
through which the weak mind of man can most effectually read his 
Creator's works, will regard with especial interest all that can tend to 
facilitate the translation of its principles into explicit practical forms.
</p>

<p>

The distinctive characteristic of the Analytical Engine, and that which has 
rendered it possible to endow mechanism with such extensive faculties as 
bid fair to make this engine the executive right-hand
of abstract algebra, is the introduction into it of the principle which 
Jacquard devised for regulating, by means of punched cards, the most 
complicated patterns in the fabrication of brocaded stuffs. It is in this that 
the distinction between the two engines lies. Nothing of the sort exists in 
the Difference Engine. We may say most aptly, that the Analytical Engine 
<em>weaves algebraical patterns</em> just as the Jacquard-loom weaves flowers and 
leaves. Here, it seems to us, resides much more of originality than the 
Difference Engine can be fairly entitled to claim. We do not wish to deny 
to this latter all such claims. We believe that it is the only proposal or 
attempt ever made to construct a calculating machine <em>founded on the 
principle of successive orders of differences</em>, and capable of <em>printing off 
its own results</em>; and that this engine surpasses its predecessors, both in the 
extent of the calculations which it can perform, in the facility, certainty and 
accuracy with which it can effect them, and in the absence of all necessity 
for the intervention of human intelligence <em>during the performance of its 
calculations</em>. Its nature is, however, limited to the strictly arithmetical, and 
it is far from being the first or only scheme for constructing <em>arithmetical</em>
calculating machines with more or less of success.
</p>

<p>

The bounds of <em>arithmetic</em> were however outstepped the moment the idea of 
applying the cards had occurred; and the Analytical Engine does not 
occupy common ground with mere &ldquo;calculating machines.&rdquo; It holds a 
position wholly its own; and the considerations it suggests are most 
interesting in their nature. In enabling mechanism to combine together 
<em>general</em> symbols in successions of unlimited variety and extent, a uniting 
link is established between the operations of matter and the abstract mental 
processes of the <em>most abstract</em> branch of mathematical science. A new, a 
vast, and a powerful language is developed for the future use of analysis, in 
which to wield its truths so that these may become of more speedy and 
accurate practical application for the purposes of mankind than the means 
hitherto in our possession have rendered possible. Thus not only the 
mental and the material, but the theoretical and the practical in the 
mathematical world, are brought into more intimate and effective 
connexion with each other. We are not aware of its being on record that 
anything partaking in the nature of what is so well designated the 
<em>Analytical</em> Engine has been hitherto proposed, or even thought of, as a 
practical possibility, any more than the idea of a thinking or of a reasoning 
machine.
</p>

<p>

We will touch on another point which constitutes an important distinction 
in the modes of operating of the Difference and Analytical Engines. In 
order to enable the former to do its business, it is necessary
to put into its columns the series of numbers constituting the first terms of 
the several orders of differences for whatever is the particular table under 
consideration. The machine then works <em>upon</em> these as its data. But these 
data must themselves have been already computed through a series of 
calculations by a human head. Therefore that engine can only produce 
results depending on data which have been arrived at by the explicit and 
actual working out of processes that are in their nature different from any 
that come within the sphere of its own powers. In other words, an 
<em>analysing</em> process must have been gone through by a human mind in order 
to obtain the data upon which the engine then <em>synthetically</em> builds its 
results. The Difference Engine is in its character exclusively <em>synthetical</em>, 
while the Analytical Engine is equally capable of analysis or of synthesis.
</p>

<p>

It is true that the Difference Engine can calculate to a much greater extent 
with these few preliminary data, than the data themselves required for their 
own determination. The table of squares, for instance, can be calculated to 
any extent whatever, when the numbers <em>one</em> and <em>two</em> are furnished; and a 
very few differences computed at any part of a table of logarithms would 
enable the engine to calculate many hundreds or even thousands of 
logarithms. Still the circumstance of its requiring, as a previous condition, 
that any function whatever shall have been numerically worked out, makes 
it very inferior in its nature and advantages to an engine which, like the 
Analytical Engine, requires merely that we should know the <em>succession 
and distribution</em> of the operations to be performed; without there
<a href="#NoteF">being 
any occasion</a>, in order to obtain data on which it can work, for our ever 
having gone through either the same particular operations which it is itself 
to effect, or any others. Numerical data must of course be given it, but they 
are mere arbitrary ones; not data that could only be arrived at through a 
systematic and necessary series of previous numerical calculations, which 
is quite a different thing.
</p>

<p>

To this it may be replied, that an analysing process must equally have been 
performed in order to furnish the Analytical Engine with the necessary 
<em>operative</em> data; and that herein may also lie a possible source of error. 
Granted that the actual mechanism is unerring in its processes, the <em>cards</em>
may give it wrong orders. This is unquestionably the case; but there is 
much less chance of error, and likewise far less expenditure of time and 
labour, where operations only, and the distribution of these operations, 
have to be made out, than where explicit numerical results are to be 
attained. In the case of the Analytical Engine we have undoubtedly to lay 
out a certain capital
of analytical labour in one particular line; but this is in order that the 
engine may bring us in a much larger return in another line. It should be 
remembered also that the cards, when once made out for any formula, 
have all the generality of algebra, and include an infinite number of 
particular cases.
</p>

<p>

We have dwelt considerably on the distinctive peculiarities of each of these 
engines, because we think it essential to place their respective attributes in 
strong relief before the apprehension of the public; and to define with 
clearness and accuracy the wholly different nature of the principles on 
which each is based, so as to make it self-evident to the reader (the 
mathematical reader at least) in what manner and degree the powers of the 
Analytical Engine transcend those of an engine, which, like the Difference 
Engine, can only work out such results as may be derived from <em>one 
restricted and particular series of processes</em>, such as those included in 
<img src="figures/adaeq22.png" align="middle" width="75" height="14" alt="\Delta^nu_z=0" />.
We think this of importance, because we know that there exists 
considerable vagueness and inaccuracy in the mind of persons in general 
on the subject. There is a misty notion amongst most of those who have 
attended at all to it, that <em>two</em> &ldquo;calculating machines&rdquo; have been successively 
invented by the same person within the last few years; while others again 
have never heard but of the one original &ldquo;calculating machine,&rdquo; and are not 
aware of there being any extension upon this. For either of these two 
classes of persons the above considerations are appropriate. While the 
latter require a knowledge of the fact that there <em>are two</em> such inventions, the 
former are not less in want of accurate and well-defined information on the 
subject. No very clear or correct ideas prevail as to the characteristics of 
each engine, or their respective advantages or disadvantages; and in 
meeting with those incidental allusions, of a more or less direct kind, which 
occur in so many publications of the day, to these machines, it must 
frequently be matter of doubt <em>which</em> &ldquo;calculating machine&rdquo; is referred to, or 
whether <em>both</em> are included in the general allusion.
</p>

<p>

We are desirous likewise of removing two misapprehensions which we 
know obtain, to some extent, respecting these engines. In the first place it 
is very generally supposed that the Difference Engine, after it had been 
completed up to a certain point, <em>suggested</em> the idea of the Analytical 
Engine; and that the second is in fact the improved offspring of the first, 
and <em>grew out</em> of the existence of its predecessor, through some natural or 
else accidental combination of ideas suggested by this one. Such a 
supposition is in this instance contrary to the facts;
although it seems to be almost an obvious inference, wherever two 
inventions, similar in their nature and objects, succeed each other
closely in order of <em>time</em>, and strikingly in order of <em>value</em>; more especially 
when the same individual is the author of both. Nevertheless the ideas 
which led to the Analytical Engine occurred in a manner wholly 
independent of any that were connected with the Difference Engine. These 
ideas are indeed in their own intrinsic nature independent of the latter 
engine, and might equally have occurred had it never existed nor been 
even thought of at all.
</p>

<p>

The second of the misapprehensions above alluded to relates to the
well-known suspension, during some years past, of all progress in the 
construction of the Difference Engine.  Respecting the circumstances which 
have interfered with the actual completion of either invention, we offer no 
opinion; and in fact are not possessed of the data for doing so, had we the 
inclination. But we know that some persons suppose these obstacles (be 
they what they may) to have arisen <em>in consequence</em> of the subsequent 
invention of the Analytical Engine while the former was in progress. We 
have ourselves heard it even <em>lamented</em> that an idea should ever have 
occurred at all, which had turned out to be merely the means of arresting 
what was already in a course of successful execution, without substituting 
the superior invention in its stead. This notion we can contradict in the 
most unqualified manner. The progress of the Difference Engine had long 
been suspended, before there were even the least crude glimmerings of any 
invention superior to it. Such glimmerings, therefore, and their subsequent 
development, were in no way the original <em>cause</em> of that suspension; 
although, where difficulties of some kind or other evidently already 
existed, it was not perhaps calculated to remove or lessen them that an 
invention should have been meanwhile thought of, which, while including 
all that the first was capable of, possesses powers so extended as to eclipse 
it altogether.
</p>

<p>

We leave it for the decision of each individual (<em>after he has possessed 
himself</em> of competent information as to the characteristics of each engine) 
to determine how far it ought to be matter of regret that such an accession 
has been made to the powers of human science, even if it <em>has</em> (which we 
greatly doubt) increased to a certain limited extent some already existing 
difficulties that had arisen in the way of completing a valuable but lesser 
work. We leave it for each to satisfy himself as to the wisdom of desiring 
the obliteration (were that now possible) of all records of the more perfect 
invention, in order that the comparatively limited one might be finished. 
The Difference Engine would doubtless fulfil all those practical objects 
which it was originally destined for. It would certainly calculate all the 
tables that are more directly necessary for the physical purposes of life, 
such as nautical and
other computations. Those who incline to very strictly utilitarian views 
may perhaps feel that the peculiar powers of the Analytical Engine bear 
upon questions of abstract and speculative science, rather than upon those 
involving every-day and ordinary human interests. These persons being 
likely to possess but little sympathy, or possibly acquaintance, with any 
branches of science which they do not find to be <em>useful</em> (according to <em>their</em>
definition of that word), may conceive that the undertaking of that engine, 
now that the other one is already in progress, would be a barren and 
unproductive laying out of yet more money and labour; in fact, a work of 
supererogation.  Even in the utilitarian aspect, however, we do not doubt 
that very valuable practical results would be developed by the extended 
faculties of the Analytical Engine; some of which results we think we 
could now hint at, had we the space; and others, which it may not yet be 
possible to foresee, but which would be brought forth by the daily 
increasing requirements of science, and by a more intimate practical 
acquaintance with the powers of the engine, were it in actual existence.
</p>

<p>

On general grounds, both of an <em>a priori</em> description as well as those 
founded on the scientific history and experience of mankind, we see strong 
presumptions that such would be the case. Nevertheless all will probably 
concur in feeling that the completion of the Difference Engine would be 
far preferable to the non-completion of any calculating engine at all. With 
whomsoever or wheresoever may rest the present causes of difficulty that 
apparently exist towards either the completion of the old engine, or the 
commencement of the new one, we trust they will not ultimately result in 
this generation's being acquainted with these inventions through the 
medium of pen, ink and paper merely;
and still more do we hope, that for the honour of our country's reputation 
in the future pages of history, these causes will not lead to the completion 
of the undertaking by some <em>other</em> nation or government. This could not but 
be matter of just regret; and equally so, whether the obstacles may have 
originated in private interests and feelings, in considerations of a more 
public description, or in causes combining the nature of both such 
solutions.
</p>

<p>

We refer the reader to the &lsquo;Edinburgh Review&rsquo; of July 1834, for a very able 
account of the Difference Engine. The writer of the article we allude to 
has selected as his prominent matter for exposition, a wholly different 
view of the subject from that which M. Menabrea has chosen. The former 
chiefly treats it under its mechanical aspect, entering but slightly into the 
mathematical principles of which that
engine is the representative, but giving, in considerable length, many 
details of the mechanism and contrivances by means of which it tabulates 
the various orders of differences. M. Menabrea, on the contrary, 
exclusively developes the analytical view; taking it for granted that
mechanism is able to perform certain processes, but without attempting to 
explain <em>how</em>; and devoting his whole attention to explanations and 
illustrations of the manner in which analytical laws can be so arranged and 
combined as to bring every branch of that vast subject within the grasp of 
the assumed powers of mechanism. It is obvious that, in the invention of a 
calculating engine, these two branches of the subject are equally essential 
fields of investigation, and that on their mutual adjustment, one to the 
other, must depend all success. They must be made to meet each other, so 
that the weak points in the powers of either department may be 
compensated by the strong points in those of the other. They are 
indissolubly connected, though so different in their intrinsic nature, that 
perhaps the same mind might not be likely to prove equally profound or 
successful in both. We know those who doubt whether the powers of 
mechanism will in practice prove adequate in all respects to the demands 
made upon them in the working of such complicated trains of machinery as 
those of the above engines, and who apprehend that unforeseen practical 
difficulties and disturbances will arise in the way of accuracy and of 
facility of operation. The Difference Engine, however, appears to us to be 
in a great measure an answer to these doubts. It is complete as far as it 
goes, and it does work with all the anticipated success. The Analytical 
Engine, far from being more complicated, will in many respects be of 
simpler construction; and it is a remarkable circumstance attending it, that 
with very <em>simplified</em> means it is so much more powerful.
</p>

<p>

The article in the &lsquo;Edinburgh Review&rsquo; was written some time previous to 
the occurrence of any ideas such as afterwards led to the invention of the 
Analytical Engine; and in the nature of the Difference Engine there is 
much less that would invite a writer to take exclusively, or even 
prominently, the mathematical view of it, than in that of the Analytical 
Engine; although mechanism has undoubtedly gone much further to meet 
mathematics, in the case of this engine, than of the former one. Some 
publication embracing the <em>mechanical</em> view of the Analytical Engine is a 
desideratum which we trust will be supplied before long.
</p>

<p>

Those who may have the patience to study a moderate quantity of rather 
dry details will find ample compensation, after perusing the article of 1834,
in the clearness with which a succinct view will have
been attained of the various practical steps through which mechanism can 
accomplish certain processes; and they will also find themselves still 
further capable of appreciating M. Menabrea's more comprehensive and 
generalized memoir. The very difference in the style and object of these 
two articles makes them peculiarly valuable to each other; at least for the 
purposes of those who really desire something more than a merely 
superficial and popular comprehension of the subject of calculating 
engines.

</p>
<p class="r">
A. A. L.
</p>

<center>
<h3><em><a name="NoteB" class="f">Note B</a></em></h3>
</center>

<p>
That portion of the Analytical Engine here alluded to is called the 
storehouse. It contains an indefinite number of the columns of discs 
described by M. Menabrea. The reader may picture to himself a pile of 
rather large draughtsmen heaped perpendicularly one above another to a 
considerable height, each counter having the digits from 0 to 9 inscribed 
on its <em>edge</em> at equal intervals; and if he then conceives that the counters do 
not actually lie one upon another so as to be in contact, but are fixed at 
small intervals of vertical distance on a common axis which passes 
perpendicularly through their centres, and around which each disc can 
<em>revolve horizontally</em> so that any required digit amongst those inscribed on 
its margin can be brought into view, he will have a good idea of one of 
these columns. The <em>lowest</em> of the discs on any column belongs to the units, 
the next above to the tens, the next above this to the hundreds, and so on. 
Thus, if we wished to inscribe 1345 on a column of the engine, it would 
stand thus:&mdash;
</p>

<center>
1<br />
3<br />
4<br />
5
</center>

<p>

In the Difference Engine there are seven of these columns placed side by 
side in a row, and the working mechanism extends behind them: the 
general form of the whole mass of machinery is that of a quadrangular 
prism (more or less approaching to the cube); the results always appearing 
on that perpendicular face of the engine which contains the columns of 
discs, opposite to which face a spectator may place himself. In the 
Analytical Engine there would be many more of these columns, probably 
at least two hundred. The precise form and arrangement which the whole 
mass of its mechanism will assume is not yet finally determined.
</p>

<p>

We may conveniently represent the columns of discs on paper in a 
diagram like the following:&mdash;
</p>


<center>
<img src="figures/noteb1.png" width="249" height="199" alt="" />
</center>

<p>

The V's are for the purpose of convenient reference to any column, either 
in writing or speaking, and are consequently numbered. The reason why 
the letter V is chosen for the purpose in preference to any other letter, is 
because these columns are designated (as the reader will find in proceeding 
with the Memoir) the <em>Variables</em>, and sometimes the <em>Variable columns</em>, or 
the <em>columns of Variables</em>. The origin of this appellation is, that the values 
on the columns are destined to change, that is to <em>vary</em>, in every conceivable 
manner. But it is necessary to guard against the natural misapprehension 
that the columns are only intended to receive the values of the <em>variables</em> in 
an analytical formula, and not of the <em>constants</em>. The columns are called 
Variables on a ground wholly unconnected with the <em>analytical</em> distinction 
between constants and variables. In order to prevent the possibility of 
confusion, we have, both in the translation and in the notes, written 
Variable with a capital letter when we use the word to signify a <em>column of 
the engine</em>, and variable with a small letter when we mean the <em>variable of a 
formula</em>. Similarly, <em>Variable-cards</em> signify any cards that belong to a 
column of the engine.
</p>

<p>

To return to the explanation of the diagram: each circle at the top is 
intended to contain the algebraic sign + or &minus;, either of which can be 
<a name="BKnote13" href="sketch_foot.html#note13">substituted</a> for the other,
according as the number represented on the 
column below is positive or negative. In a similar manner any other purely 
<em>symbolical</em> results of algebraical processes might be made
to appear in these circles. In <a href="#NoteA">Note A.</a>
the practicability of developing 
<em>symbolical</em> with no less ease than <em>numerical</em> results has been touched on. 
The zeros beneath the <em>symbolic</em> circles represent each of them a disc, 
supposed to have the digit 0 presented in front. Only four tiers of zeros 
have been figured in the diagram, but these may be considered as 
representing thirty or forty, or any number of tiers of discs that may be 
required. Since each disc can present any digit, and each circle any sign, 
the discs of every column may be <a name="BKnote14" href="sketch_foot.html#note14">so adjusted</a>
as to express any positive 
or negative number whatever within the limits of the machine; which limits 
depend on the <em>perpendicular</em> extent of the mechanism, that is, on the 
number of discs to a column.
</p>

<p>

Each of the squares below the zeros is intended for the inscription of any 
<em>general</em> symbol or combination of symbols we please; it being understood 
that the number represented on the column immediately above is the 
numerical value of that symbol, or combination of symbols. Let us, for 
instance, represent the three quantities <em>a</em>, <em>n</em>, <em>x</em>,
and let us further suppose 
that <em>a</em> = 5, <em>n</em> = 7, <em>x</em> = 98. We should have&mdash;
</p>


<map name="noteb2" id="noteb2">
<area shape="rect" coords="13,20,51,68" href="sketch_foot.html#note15" alt="Footnote" />
</map>
<center>
<a class="i" name="BKnote15" href="sketch_foot.html#note15">
<img src="figures/noteb2.png" usemap="#noteb2" border="0" width="283" height="214" alt="" />
</a>
<br />
<font size="-1" face="Helvetica"><a href="sketch_foot.html#note15">Read footnote</a></font>.
</center>

<p>

We may now combine these symbols in a variety of ways, so as to form 
any required function or functions of them, and we may then inscribe each 
such function below brackets, every bracket uniting together those 
quantities (and those only) which enter into the function inscribed below 
it. We must also, when we have decided on the particular function whose 
numerical value we desire to calculate, assign another column to the
right-hand for receiving the <em>results</em>, and must inscribe the function in the square 
below this column. In the above instance we might have any one of the 
following functions:&mdash;
</p>

<center>
<img src="figures/adaeq4.png" width="412" height="24"
     alt="$ax^n$, $x^{an}$, $a\cdot n\cdot x$, $\frac{a}{n}x$, $a+n+x$, \&amp;c. \&amp;.c" />
</center>
<p>

Let us select the first. It would stand as follows, previous to calculation:&mdash;
</p>

<center>
<img src="figures/noteb3.png" width="299" height="266" alt="" />
</center>

<p>

The data being given, we must now put into the engine the cards proper 
for directing the operations in the case of the particular function chosen. 
These operations would in this instance be,&mdash;
</p>

<p>

First, six multiplications in order to get <em>x<sup>n</sup></em>
(=98<sup>7</sup> for the above particular 
data).
</p>

<p>

Secondly, one multiplication in order then to get <em>a&middot;x<sup>n</sup></em> (=5&middot;98<sup>7</sup>).
</p>

<p>

In all, seven multiplications to complete the whole process. We may thus 
represent them:&mdash;
</p>

<center>
(&times;, &times;, &times;, &times;, &times;, &times;, &times;), or 7 (&times;).
</center>

<p>

The multiplications would, however, at successive stages in the solution of 
the problem, operate on pairs of numbers, derived from <em>different</em> columns. 
In other words, the <em>same operation</em> would be performed on different 
<em>subjects of operation</em>. And here again is an illustration of the remarks 
made in the <a href="#NoteA">preceding Note</a> on the independent manner in which the 
engine directs its <em>operations</em>. In determining the
value of <em>ax<sup>n</sup></em>, the 
<em>operations</em> are <em>homogeneous</em>, but are distributed amongst different 
<em>subjects of operation</em>, at successive stages of the computation. It is by 
means of certain punched cards, belonging to the Variables themselves, 
that the action of the operations is so <em>distributed</em> as to suit each particular 
function. The <em>Operation-cards</em> merely determine the succession of 
operations in a general manner. They in fact throw all that portion of the 
mechanism included in the <em>mill</em> into a series of different <em>states</em>, which we 
may call the <em>adding state</em>, or the <em>multiplying state</em>, &amp;c. respectively. In 
each of these states the mechanism is ready to act in the way peculiar to 
that state, on any pair of numbers which may be permitted to come within 
its sphere of action. Only <em>one</em> of these operating states of the mill can exist 
at a time; and the nature of the mechanism is also such that only <em>one pair 
of numbers</em> can be received
and acted on at a time. Now, in order to secure that the mill shall receive a 
constant supply of the proper pairs of numbers in succession, and that it 
shall also rightly locate the result of an operation performed upon any pair, 
each Variable has cards of its own belonging to it. It has, first, a class of 
cards whose business it is to <em>allow</em> the number on the Variable to pass into 
the mill, there to be operated upon. These cards may be called the 
<em>Supplying-cards</em>. They furnish the mill with its proper food. Each 
Variable has, secondly, another class of cards, whose office it is to allow 
the Variable to <em>receive</em> a number <em>from</em> the mill. These cards may be called 
the <em>Receiving-cards</em>. <em>They</em> regulate the location of results, whether 
temporary or ultimate results. The Variable-cards in general (including 
both the preceding classes) might, it appears to us, be even more 
appropriately designated the Distributive-cards, since it is through their 
means that the action of the operations, and the results of this action, are 
rightly <em>distributed</em>.
</p>

<p>

There are <em>two varieties</em> of the <em>Supplying</em> Variable-cards, respectively 
adapted for fulfilling two distinct subsidiary purposes: but as these 
modifications do not bear upon the present subject, we shall notice them in 
another place.
</p>

<p>

In the above case of <em>ax<sup>n</sup></em>, the Operation-cards merely order seven 
multiplications, that is, they order the mill to be in the <em>multiplying state</em> 
seven successive times (without any reference to the particular columns 
whose numbers are to be acted upon). The proper Distributive
Variable-cards step in at each successive multiplication, and cause the distributions 
requisite for the particular case.
</p>

<center>
<img src="figures/adaeq5.png" width="480" height="76" alt="" />
</center>
<p>

The engine might be made to calculate all these in succession. Having 
completed <em>ax<sup>n</sup></em>, the function
<em>x<sup>an</sup></em> might be written under the brackets 
instead of <em>ax<sup>n</sup></em>, and a new calculation commenced (the appropriate 
Operation and Variable-cards for the new function of course coming into 
play). The results would then appear on V<sub>5</sub>. So on for any number of 
different functions of the quantities <em>a</em>, <em>n</em>, <em>x</em>.
Each <em>result</em> might either
permanently remain on its column during the succeeding calculations, so 
that when all the functions had been computed, their values would 
simultaneously exist on V<sub>4</sub>, V<sub>5</sub>, V<sub>6</sub>, &amp;c.; or each result might (after being 
printed off, or used in any specified manner) be effaced, to make way for 
its successor. The square under V<sub>4</sub> ought,
for the latter arrangement, to have the functions
<em>ax<sup>n</sup></em>, <em>x<sup>an</sup></em>, <em>anx</em>, &amp;c.
successively inscribed in it.
</p>

<p>

Let us now suppose that we have <em>two</em> expressions whose values have been 
computed by the engine independently of each other (each having its own 
group of columns for data and results). Let them be <em>ax<sup>n</sup></em>,
and <em>bpy</em>. They 
would then stand as follows on the columns:&mdash;
</p>

<center>
<img src="figures/noteb4.png" width="575" height="258" alt="" />
</center>

<p>

We may now desire to combine together these two <em>results</em>, in any manner 
we please; in which case it would only be necessary to have an additional 
card or cards, which should order the requisite operations to be performed 
with the numbers on the two result-columns V<sub>4</sub> and V<sub>8</sub>,
and the <em>result of 
these further operations</em> to appear on a new column, V<sub>9</sub>. Say that we wish 
to divide <em>ax<sup>n</sup></em> by <em>bpy</em>. The numerical value of this division would then 
appear on the column V<sub>9</sub>, beneath which we have inscribed
<img src="figures/noteb5.png" align="middle" width="30" height="33" alt="$\frac{ax^n}{bpy}$" />.
The whole series of operations from the beginning would be as follows (<em>n</em> being 
= 7):
</p>


<center>
{7(&times;), 2(&times;), &divide;}, or {9(&times;), &divide;}.
</center>

<p>

This example is introduced merely to show that we may, if we please, 
retain separately and permanently any <em>intermediate</em>
results (like <em>ax<sup>n</sup></em>, <em>bpy</em>) 
which occur in the course of processes having an ulterior and more 
complicated result as their chief and final object
<font size="+4">(</font>like <img src="figures/noteb5.png" align="bottom" width="30" height="33" alt="\frac{ax^n}{bpy}" /><font size="+4">)</font>.
</p>

<p>

Any group of columns may be considered as representing a <em>general</em>
function, until a <em>special</em> one has been implicitly impressed upon them 
through the introduction into the engine of the Operation and
Variable-cards made out for a <em>particular</em> function.
Thus, in the preceding example, 
V<sub>1</sub>, V<sub>2</sub>, V<sub>3</sub>, V<sub>5</sub>, V<sub>6</sub>, V<sub>7</sub>
represent the <em>general</em> function
&Phi;(<em>a</em>, <em>n</em>, <em>b</em>, <em>p</em>, <em>x</em>, <em>y</em>) 
until the function <img src="figures/noteb5.png" align="middle" width="30" height="34" alt="$\frac{ax^n}{bpy}$" /> has been determined on, and
<em>implicitly</em> expressed by the placing of the right cards in the engine. The 
actual working of the mechanism, as regulated by these cards, then 
<em>explicitly</em> developes the value of the function. The inscription of a function 
under the brackets, and in the square under the result-column, in no way 
influences the processes or the results, and is merely a memorandum for 
the observer, to remind him of what is going on.  It is the Operation and the 
Variable-cards only which in reality determine the function.  Indeed it 
should be distinctly kept in mind, that the inscriptions within <em>any</em> of the 
squares are quite independent of the mechanism or workings of the engine, 
and are nothing but arbitrary memorandums placed there at pleasure to 
assist the spectator.
</p>

<p>

The further we analyse the manner in which such an engine performs its 
processes and attains its results, the more we perceive how distinctly it 
places in a true and just light the mutual relations and connexion of the 
various steps of mathematical analysis; how clearly it separates those 
things which are in reality distinct and independent, and unites those 
which are mutually dependent.
</p>

<p class="r">
A. A. L.
</p>

<center>
<h3><em><a name="NoteC" class="f">Note C</a></em></h3>
</center>

<p>
Those who may desire to study the principles of the Jacquard-loom in the 
most effectual manner, viz. that of practical observation, have only to step 
into the Adelaide Gallery or the Polytechnic Institution. In each of these 
valuable repositories of scientific <em>illustration</em>, a weaver is constantly 
working at a Jacquard-loom, and is ready to give any information that may 
be desired as to the construction and modes of acting of his apparatus. The 
volume on the manufacture of silk, in Lardner's Cyclop&aelig;dia, contains a 
chapter on the Jacquard-loom, which may also be consulted with 
advantage.
</p>

<p>

The mode of application of the cards, as hitherto used in the art of 
weaving, was not found, however, to be sufficiently powerful for all the 
simplifications which it was desirable to attain in such varied and 
complicated processes as those required in order to fulfil the purposes of 
an Analytical Engine. A method was devised of what was technically 
designated <em>backing</em> the cards in certain groups according to certain laws. 
The object of this extension is to secure the possibility of bringing any 
particular card or set of cards into use <em>any number of times successively</em> in 
the solution of one problem. Whether this power shall be taken advantage 
of or not, in each particular instance, will depend on the nature of the 
operations which the problem under consideration may require. The 
process is <a href="#menaref2">alluded to by M. Menabrea</a>, and it is a very 
important simplification. It has been
proposed to use it for the reciprocal benefit of that art, which, while it has 
itself no apparent connexion with the domains of abstract science, has yet 
proved so valuable to the latter, in suggesting the principles which, in their 
new and singular field of application, seem likely to place <em>algebraical</em> 
combinations not less completely within the province of mechanism, than 
are all those varied intricacies of which <em>intersecting threads</em> are 
susceptible. By the introduction of the system of <em>backing</em> into the 
Jacquard-loom itself, patterns which should possess symmetry, and follow 
regular laws of any extent, might be woven by means of comparatively few 
cards.
</p>

<p>

Those who understand the mechanism of this loom will perceive that the 
above improvement is easily effected in practice, by causing the prism 
over which the train of pattern-cards is suspended to revolve <em>backwards</em>
instead of <em>forwards</em>, at pleasure, under the requisite circumstances; until, 
by so doing, any particular card, or set of cards, that has done duty once, 
and passed on in the ordinary regular succession, is brought back to the 
position it occupied just before it was used the preceding time. The prism 
then resumes its <em>forward</em> rotation, and thus brings the card or set of cards 
in question into play a second time. This process may obviously be 
repeated any number of times.

</p>
<p class="r">
A. A. L.
</p>

<center>
<h3><em><a name="NoteD" class="f">Note D</a></em></h3>
</center>

<p>
We have represented the solution of these two equations below, with every detail, 
in a diagram similar to those used in <a href="#NoteB">Note B</a>;
but additional explanations 
are requisite, partly in order to make this more complicated case perfectly 
clear, and partly for the comprehension of certain indications and 
notations not used in the preceding diagrams. Those who may wish to 
understand <a href="#NoteG">Note G</a> completely, are recommended to pay particular 
attention to the contents of the present Note, or they will not otherwise 
comprehend the similar notation and indications when applied to a much 
more complicated case.
</p>

<center>
<table>
<tr>
<td>
<a class="i" href="figures/menat5_l.png">
<!-- ./textogif -dpi 88 menat5 -->
<img src="figures/menat5.png" width="639" height="355" alt="" />
</a>
</td></tr>
<tr>
<td width="639">
<font size="-1" face="Helvetica">Clicking on the diagram displays a larger image of it.
Your browser's &ldquo;Back&rdquo; button will return you to this document.
A ready to print PostScript file for this diagram is also
<a href="figures/menat5ps.zip">available for downloading</a> in
a ZIP compressed archive.
</font>
</td></tr>
</table>
</center>

<p>

In all calculations, the columns of Variables used may be divided into 
three classes:&mdash;
</p>

<p>

&nbsp;&nbsp;1st. Those on which the data are inscribed:<br />
&nbsp;&nbsp;2ndly. Those intended to receive the final results:<br />
&nbsp;&nbsp;3rdly. Those intended to receive such intermediate and temporary 
combinations of the primitive data as are not to be permanently retained, 
but are merely needed for <em>working with</em>, in order to attain the ultimate 
results. Combinations of this kind might properly be called
<em>secondary data</em>. They are in fact so many <em>successive stages</em> towards the 
final result. The columns which receive them are rightly named
<em>Working-Variables</em>, for their office is in its nature
purely <em>subsidiary</em> to other 
purposes. They develope an intermediate and transient class of results, 
which unite the original data with the final results.
</p>

<p>

The Result-Variables sometimes partake of the nature of
Working-Variables. It frequently happens that a Variable destined to receive a final 
result is the recipient of one or more intermediate values successively, in 
the course of the processes. Similarly, the Variables for data often become 
Working-Variables, or Result-Variables, or even both in succession. It so 
happens, however, that in the case of the present equations the three sets of 
offices remain throughout perfectly separate and independent.
</p>

<p>

It will be observed, that in the squares below the <em>Working</em>-Variables 
nothing is inscribed. Any one of these Variables is in many cases destined 
to pass through various values successively during the performance of a 
calculation (although in these particular equations no instance of this 
occurs) . Consequently no <em>one fixed</em> symbol, or combination of symbols, 
should be considered as properly belonging to a merely
<em>Working</em>-Variable; and as a general rule their squares are left blank. Of course in 
this, as in all other cases where we mention a <em>general</em> rule, it is 
understood that many particular exceptions may be expedient.
</p>

<p>

In order that all the indications contained in the diagram may be 
completely understood, we shall now explain two or three points, not 
hitherto touched on. When the value on any Variable is called into use, 
one of two consequences may be made to result. Either the value may 
<em>return</em> to the Variable after it has been used, in which case it is ready for a 
second use if needed; or the Variable may be made zero. (We are of 
course not considering a third case, of not unfrequent occurrence, in which 
the same Variable is destined to receive the <em>result</em> of the very operation 
which it has just supplied with a number.) Now the ordinary rule is, that 
the value <em>returns</em> to the Variable; unless it has been foreseen that no use 
for that value can recur, in which case zero is substituted. At the <em>end</em> of a 
calculation, therefore, every column ought as a general rule to be zero, 
excepting those for results. Thus it will be seen by the diagram, that when 
<em>m</em>, the value on V<sub>0</sub>, is used for the second time by Operation 5,
V<sub>0</sub>
becomes 0, since <em>m</em> is not again needed; that similarly, when
(<em>mn'</em> &minus; <em>m'n</em>), 
on V<sub>12</sub>, is used for the third time by Operation 11, V<sub>12</sub> becomes zero, 
since (<em>mn'</em> &minus; <em>m'n</em>) is not again needed. In order to provide for the one or the 
other of the courses above indicated, there are <em>two</em> varieties of the 
<em>Supplying</em> Variable-cards. One of these varieties has provisions which 
cause
the number given off from any Variable to <em>return</em> to that Variable after 
doing its duty in the mill. The other variety has provisions which cause 
<em>zero</em> to be substituted on the Variable, for the number given off. These two 
varieties are distinguished, when needful, by the respective appellations of 
the <em>Retaining</em> Supply-cards and the <em>Zero</em> Supply-cards. We see that 
the primary office (see <a href="#NoteB">Note B</a>.) of both these varieties of cards is the 
same; they only differ in their <em>secondary</em> office.
</p>

<p>

Every Variable thus has belonging to it one class of <em>Receiving</em>
Variable-cards and <em>two</em> classes of <em>Supplying</em> Variable-cards.
It is plain however that 
only the <em>one</em> or the <em>other</em> of these two latter classes can be used by any one 
Variable for one operation; never <em>both</em> simultaneously, their respective 
functions being mutually incompatible.
</p>

<p>

It should be understood that the Variable-cards are not placed in 
<em>immediate contiguity</em> with the columns. Each card is connected by means 
of wires with the column it is intended to act upon.
</p>

<p>

Our diagram ought in reality to be placed side by side with M. Menabrea's 
corresponding table, so as to be compared with it, line for line belonging 
to each operation. But it was unfortunately inconvenient to print them in 
this desirable form. The diagram is, in the main, merely another manner of 
indicating the various relations denoted in M. Menabrea's table. Each 
mode has some advantages and some disadvantages. Combined, they form 
a complete and accurate method of registering every step and sequence in 
all calculations performed by the engine.
</p>

<p>

No notice has yet been taken of the <em>upper</em> indices which are added to the 
left of each V in the diagram; an addition which we have also taken the 
liberty of making to the V's in M. Menabrea's tables <a href="#menaref3">3</a>
and <a href="#menaref4">4</a>, 
since it does not <em>alter</em> anything therein represented by him, but merely 
<em>adds</em> something to the previous indications of those tables. The <em>lower</em>
indices are obviously indices of <em>locality</em> only, and are wholly independent 
of the operations performed or of the results obtained, their value 
continuing unchanged during the performance of calculations. The <em>upper</em>
indices, however, are of a different nature. Their office is to indicate any 
<em>alteration</em> in the value which a Variable represents; and they are of course 
liable to changes during the processes of a calculation. Whenever a 
Variable has only zeros upon it, it is called <sup>0</sup>V; the moment a value 
appears on it (whether that value be placed there arbitrarily, or appears in 
the natural course of a calculation), it becomes <sup>1</sup>V. If this value gives 
place to another value, the Variable becomes <sup>2</sup>V, and so forth. Whenever a 
<em>value</em> again gives place to <em>zero</em>, the Variable again becomes <sup>0</sup>V, even if it 
have been <sup>n</sup>V the moment before. If a <em>value</em> then again be substituted, the 
Variable
becomes <sup>n+1</sup>V (as it would have done if it had not passed through the 
intermediate <sup>0</sup>V); &amp;c. &amp;c. Just before any calculation is commenced, and 
after the data have been given, and everything adjusted and prepared for 
setting the mechanism in action, the upper indices of the Variables for data 
are all unity, and those for the Working and Result-variables are all zero. In 
this state the diagram <a name="BKnote16" href="sketch_foot.html#note16">represents them</a>.
</p>

<p>

There are several advantages in having a set of indices of this nature; but 
these advantages are perhaps hardly of a kind to be immediately perceived, 
unless by a mind somewhat accustomed to trace the successive steps by 
means of which the engine accomplishes its purposes. We have only space 
to mention in a general way, that the whole notation of the tables is made 
more consistent by these indices, for they are able to mark a <em>difference</em> in 
certain cases, where there would otherwise be an apparent <em>identity</em>
confusing in its tendency. In such a case as
V<sub><em>n</em></sub>=V<sub><em>p</em></sub>+V<sub><em>n</em></sub> there is more 
clearness and more consistency with the usual laws of algebraical notation, 
in being able to write
<sup><em>m+1</em></sup>V<sub><em>n</em></sub>=<sup><em>q</em></sup>V<sub><em>p</em></sub>+<sup><em>m</em></sup>V<sub><em>n</em></sub>.
It is also obvious that the indices 
furnish a powerful means of tracing back the derivation of any result; and 
of registering various circumstances concerning that <em>series of successive 
substitutions</em>, of which every <em>result</em> is in fact merely the final consequence; 
circumstances that may in certain cases involve relations which it is 
important to observe, either for purely analytical reasons, or for practically 
adapting the workings of the engine to their occurrence. The series of 
substitutions which lead to the equations of the diagram are as follow:&mdash;
</p>

<map name="noted1" id="noted1">
<area shape="rect" coords="16,16,48,48" href="sketch_foot.html#note16" alt="Footnote 16" />
</map>
<center>
<a class="i" href="sketch_foot.html#note16">
<img src="figures/noted1.png" usemap="#noted1" border="0" width="550" height="129" alt="" />
</a>
<br />
<font size="-1" face="Helvetica"><a href="sketch_foot.html#note16">Read footnote</a></font>.
</center>

<p>

There are <em>three</em> successive substitutions for each of these equations. The 
formul&aelig; (2.), (3.) and (4.) are <em>implicitly</em> contained in (1.), which latter we 
may consider as being in fact the <em>condensed</em> expression of any of the 
former. It will be observed that every succeeding substitution must contain 
<em>twice</em> as many V's as its predecessor. So that if a problem
require <em>n</em> substitutions, the successive series of numbers for the V's in the 
whole of them will be 2, 4, 8, 16&hellip;2<sup>n</sup>.
</p>

<p>

The substitutions in the preceding equations happen to be of little value 
towards illustrating the power and uses of the upper indices, for, owing to 
the nature of these particular equations, the indices are all unity 
throughout. We wish we had space to enter more fully into the relations 
which these indices would in many cases enable us to trace.
</p>

<p>

M. Menabrea incloses the three centre columns of his table under the 
general title <em>Variable-cards</em>. The V's however in reality all represent the 
actual <em>Variable-columns</em> of the engine, and not the cards that belong to 
them. Still the title is a very just one, since it is through the special action 
of certain Variable-cards (when <em>combined</em> with the more generalized 
agency of the Operation-cards) that every one of the particular relations he 
has indicated under that title is brought about.
</p>

<p>

Suppose we wish to ascertain how often any <em>one</em> quantity, or combination 
of quantities, is brought into use during a calculation. We easily ascertain 
<em>this</em>, from the inspection of any vertical column or columns of the diagram 
in which that quantity may appear. Thus, in the present case, we see that all 
the data, and all the intermediate results likewise, are used twice, excepting 
(<em>mn'</em> &minus; <em>m'n</em>), which is used three times.
</p>

<p>

The <em>order</em> in which it is possible to perform the operations for the present 
example, enables us to effect all the eleven operations of which it consists 
with only <em>three Operation cards</em>; because the problem is of such a nature 
that it admits of each <em>class</em> of operations being performed in a group 
together; all the multiplications one after another, all the subtractions one 
after another, &amp;c. The operations are {6(&times;), 3(-), 2(&divide;)}.
</p>

<p>

Since the very definition of an operation implies that there must be <em>two</em>
numbers to act upon, there are of course <em>two Supplying</em> Variable-cards 
necessarily brought into action for every operation, in order to furnish the 
two proper numbers. (See <a href="#NoteB">Note B</a>.) Also, since every operation must 
produce a <em>result</em>, which must be placed <em>somewhere</em>,
each operation entails 
the action of a <em>Receiving</em> Variable-card, to indicate the proper locality for 
the result. Therefore, at least three times as many Variable-cards as there 
are <em>operations</em> (not <em>Operation-cards</em>, for these, as we have just seen, are 
by no means always as numerous as the <em>operations</em>) are brought into use in 
every calculation. Indeed, under certain contingencies, a still larger 
proportion is requisite; such, for example, would probably be the case 
when the same result has to appear on more than one Variable 
simultaneously (which is not unfrequently a provision necessary for 
subsequent purposes in a calculation), and in some other cases which we 
shall not here specify.
We see therefore that a great disproportion exists between the amount of 
<em>Variable</em> and of <em>Operation</em>-cards requisite for the working of even the 
simplest calculation.
</p>

<p>

<em>All</em> calculations do not admit, like this one, of the operations of the same 
nature being performed in groups together. Probably very few do so 
without exceptions occurring in one or other stage of the progress; and 
some would not admit it at all. The <em>order</em> in which the operations shall be 
performed in every particular case is a very interesting and curious 
question, on which our space does not permit us fully to enter. In almost 
every computation a great <em>variety</em> of arrangements for the succession of 
the processes is possible, and various considerations must influence the 
selection amongst them for the purposes of a Calculating Engine. One 
essential object is to choose that arrangement which shall tend to reduce to 
a minimum the <em>time</em> necessary for completing the calculation.
</p>

<p>

It must be evident how multifarious and how mutually complicated are the 
considerations which the working of such an engine involve. There are 
frequently several distinct <em>sets of effects</em> going on simultaneously; all in a 
manner independent of each other, and yet to a greater or less degree 
exercising a mutual influence. To adjust each to every other, and indeed 
even to perceive and trace them out with perfect correctness and success, 
entails difficulties whose nature partakes to a certain extent of those 
involved in every question where <em>conditions</em> are very numerous and
inter-complicated; such as for instance the estimation of the mutual relations 
amongst <em>statistical</em> ph&aelig;nomena, and of those involved in many other 
classes of facts.
</p>

<p class="r">
A. A. L.
</p>

<center>
<h3><em><a name="NoteE" class="f">Note E</a></em></h3>
</center>

<p>
This example has evidently been chosen on account of its brevity and 
simplicity, with a view merely to explain the <em>manner</em> in which the engine 
would proceed in the case of an <em>analytical calculation containing 
variables</em>, rather than to illustrate the <em>extent of its powers</em> to solve cases of 
a difficult and complex nature. The equations <a href="#menaref5">in first example in the Memoir</a>
are in fact a 
more complicated problem than the present one.
</p>

<p>

We have not subjoined any diagram of its development for this new 
example, as we did for the former one, because this is unnecessary after 
the full application already made of those diagrams to the illustration of 
M. Menabrea's excellent tables.
</p>

<p>

It may be remarked that a slight discrepancy exists between the formul&aelig;
</p>

<center>
(<em>a</em> + <em>bx</em><sup>1</sup>)<br />
(A + B cos<sup>1</sup> <em>x</em>)
</center>

<p>

given in the Memoir as the <em>data</em> for calculation,
and the <em>results</em> of the 
calculation as developed in the last division of the table which 
accompanies it. To agree perfectly with this latter, the data should have 
been given as
</p>

<center>
(<em>ax</em><sup>0</sup> + <em>bx</em><sup>1</sup>)<br />
(A cos<sup>0</sup> <em>x</em> + B cos<sup>1</sup> <em>x</em>)
</center>

<p>

The following is a more complicated example of the manner in which the 
engine would compute a trigonometrical function containing variables. To 
multiply
</p>

<table width="100%">
<tr>
<td align="left" width="30%">&nbsp;</td>
<td align="left" width="70%">A+A<sub>1</sub>cos&nbsp;<em>&theta;</em>
    + A<sub>2</sub>cos&nbsp;2<em>&theta;</em>
    + A<sub>3</sub>cos&nbsp;3<em>&theta;</em> + &middot;&middot;&middot;</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" width="30%">by</td>
<td align="left" width="70%">B + B<sub>1</sub>cos&nbsp;<em>&theta;</em>.</td>
</tr>
</table>

<p>

Let the resulting products be represented under 
the general form
</p>

<table>
<tr>
<td align="center" width="99%">C<sub>0</sub> + C<sub>1</sub>cos&nbsp;<em>&theta;</em> +
    C<sub>2</sub>cos&nbsp;2<em>&theta;</em> +
    C<sub>3</sub>cos&nbsp;3<em>&theta;</em> + &middot;&middot;&middot;</td>
<td align="right" width="1%">(1.)</td>
</tr>
</table>

<p>

This trigonometrical series is not only in itself very appropriate for 
illustrating the processes of the engine, but is likewise of much practical 
interest from its frequent use in astronomical computations. Before 
proceeding further with it, we shall point out that there are three very 
distinct classes of ways in which it may be desired to deduce numerical 
values from any analytical formula.
</p>

<p>

First. We may wish to find the collective numerical value of the <em>whole 
formula</em>, without any reference to the quantities of which that formula is a 
function, or to the particular mode of their combination and distribution, 
of which the formula is the result and representative. Values of this kind 
are of a strictly arithmetical nature in the most limited sense of the term, 
and retain no trace whatever of the processes through which they have 
been deduced. In fact, any one such numerical value may have been 
attained from an <em>infinite variety</em> of data, or of problems.
The values for <em>x</em>
and <em>y</em> in the two equations (see <a href="#NoteD">Note D</a>.)
come under this class of 
numerical results.
</p>

<p>

Secondly. We may propose to compute the collective numerical value of 
<em>each term</em> of a formula, or of a series, and to keep these results separate. 
The engine must in such a case appropriate as many columns to <em>results</em> as 
there are terms to compute.
</p>

<p>

Thirdly. It may be desired to compute the numerical value of various 
<em>subdivisions of each term</em>, and to keep all these results separate.
It may be
required, for instance, to compute each coefficient separately from its 
variable, in which particular case the engine must appropriate <em>two</em>
result-columns to <em>every term that contains both a variable and coefficient</em>.
</p>

<p>

There are many ways in which it may be desired in special cases
to distribute and keep separate the numerical values of different parts of an 
algebraical formula; and the power of effecting such distributions to any 
extent is essential to the <em>algebraical</em> character of the Analytical Engine. 
Many persons who are not conversant with mathematical studies, imagine 
that because the business of the engine is to give its results in <em>numerical 
notation</em>, the <em>nature of its processes</em> must consequently
be <em>arithmetical</em> and 
<em>numerical</em>, rather than <em>algebraical</em> and <em>analytical</em>.
This is an error. The 
engine can arrange and combine its numerical quantities exactly as if they 
were <em>letters</em> or any other <em>general</em> symbols; and in fact it might bring out its 
results in algebraical <em>notation</em>, were provisions made accordingly. It might 
develope three sets of results simultaneously, viz. <em>symbolic</em> results (as 
already alluded to in Notes <a href="#NoteA">A</a>. and <a href="#NoteB">B</a>.),
<em>numerical</em> results (its chief and 
primary object); and <em>algebraical</em> results in <em>literal</em> notation.
This latter 
however has not been deemed a necessary or desirable addition to its 
powers, partly because the necessary arrangements for effecting it would 
increase the complexity and extent of the mechanism to a degree that 
would not be commensurate with the advantages, where the main object of 
the invention is to translate into <em>numerical</em> language general formul&aelig; of 
analysis already known to us, or whose laws of formation are known to us. 
But it would be a mistake to suppose that because its <em>results</em> are given in 
the <em>notation</em> of a more restricted science, its <em>processes</em> are therefore 
restricted to those of that science. The object of the engine is in fact to give 
the <em>utmost practical efficiency</em> to the resources of
<em>numerical interpretations</em> of the higher science of analysis,
while it uses the processes and 
combinations of this latter.
</p>

<p>

To return to the trigonometrical series. We shall only consider the first 
four terms of the factor (A + A<sub>1</sub> cos&nbsp;<em>&theta;</em> + &amp;c.), since this will be sufficient to 
show the method. We propose to obtain separately the numerical value of 
<em>each coefficient</em> C<sub>0</sub>, C<sub>1</sub>, &amp;c. of (1.). The direct multiplication of the two 
factors gives
</p>

<table>
<tr>
<td align="center" width="99%"><img src="figures/adaeq6.png" width="574" height="37" alt="" /></td>
<td align="right" width="1%">(2.)</td>
</tr>
</table>

<p>

a result which would stand thus on the engine:&mdash;
</p>

<center>
<img src="figures/notee1.png" width="529" height="131" alt="" />
</center>

<p />

<center>
<!-- ./textogif -dpi 120 notee2 -->
<img src="figures/notee2.png" width="592" height="108" alt="" />
</center>

<p>

The variable belonging to each coefficient is written below it, as we have 
done in the diagram, by way of memorandum. The only further reduction 
which is at first apparently possible in the preceding result, would be the 
addition of V<sub>21</sub> to V<sub>31</sub> (in which
case B<sub>1</sub>A should be effaced from V<sub>31</sub>). 
The whole operations from the beginning
would then be&mdash;
</p>

<center>
<table width="100%">
<tr>
<td align="center" width="30%"><em>First Series of <br />Operations</em></td>
<td align="center" width="30%"><em>Second Series of <br />Operations</em></td>
<td align="center" width="40%"><em>Third Series, which contains<br /> only one (final) operation</em></td>
</tr>
<tr>
    <td align="center"><sup>1</sup>V<sub>10</sub>&times;<sup>1</sup>V<sub>0</sub>&nbsp;=&nbsp;<sup>1</sup>V<sub>20</sub></td>
    <td align="center"><sup>1</sup>V<sub>11</sub>&times;<sup>1</sup>V<sub>0</sub>&nbsp;=&nbsp;<sup>1</sup>V<sub>31</sub></td>
    <td align="center"><sup>1</sup>V<sub>21</sub>&times;<sup>1</sup>V<sub>31</sub>&nbsp;=&nbsp;<sup>2</sup>V<sub>21</sub>, and</td>
</tr>

<tr>
    <td align="center"><sup>1</sup>V<sub>10</sub>&times;<sup>1</sup>V<sub>1</sub>&nbsp;=&nbsp;<sup>1</sup>V<sub>21</sub></td>
    <td align="center"><sup>1</sup>V<sub>11</sub>&times;<sup>1</sup>V<sub>1</sub>&nbsp;=&nbsp;<sup>1</sup>V<sub>32</sub></td>
    <td align="center">V<sub>31</sub> becomes = 0.</td>
</tr>

<tr>
    <td align="center"><sup>1</sup>V<sub>10</sub>&times;<sup>1</sup>V<sub>2</sub>&nbsp;=&nbsp;<sup>1</sup>V<sub>22</sub></td>
    <td align="center"><sup>1</sup>V<sub>11</sub>&times;<sup>1</sup>V<sub>2</sub>&nbsp;=&nbsp;<sup>1</sup>V<sub>33</sub></td>
</tr>

<tr>
    <td align="center"><sup>1</sup>V<sub>10</sub>&times;<sup>1</sup>V<sub>3</sub>&nbsp;=&nbsp;<sup>1</sup>V<sub>23</sub></td>
    <td align="center"><sup>1</sup>V<sub>11</sub>&times;<sup>1</sup>V<sub>3</sub>&nbsp;=&nbsp;<sup>1</sup>V<sub>34</sub></td>
</tr>

</table>
</center>

<p>

We do not enter into the same detail of <em>every</em> step of the processes as in the 
examples of Notes <a href="#NoteD">D</a>. and <a href="#NoteG">G</a>.,
thinking it unnecessary and tedious to do so. 
The reader will remember the meaning and use of the upper and lower 
indices, &amp;c., as before explained.
</p>

<p>

To proceed: we know that
</p>

<table>
<tr>
<td align="center" width="99%"><img src="figures/adaeq7.png" width="371" height="28" 
    alt="\cos n\theta\cdot\cos\theta = \frac{1}{2}\cos \overline{n+1}\theta +\frac{1}{2}\overline{n-1}\theta" /></td>
<td align="right" width="1%">(3.)</td>
</tr>
</table>

<p>

Consequently, a slight examination of the second line of (2.)
will show that by making the proper substitutions, (2.) will become
</p>

<!--  ./textogif -dpi 140 adaeq16
      Then cut the two pieces out and save as adaeq16a and adaeq16b  -->
<center>
<img src="figures/adaeq16a.png" width="623" height="116" alt="" />
</center>

<p>

These coefficients should respectively appear on
</p>

<center>
<img src="figures/adaeq16b.png" width="624" height="15" alt="" />
</center>

<p>

We shall perceive, if we inspect the particular arrangement of the
results in (2.) on the Result-columns as represented in the diagram,
that, in order to effect this transformation, each successive coefficient
upon V<sub>32</sub>, V<sub>33</sub>, &amp;c. (beginning with V<sub>32</sub>),
must through means of proper 
cards be divided by
<em><a name="BKnote17" href="sketch_foot.html#note17">two</a></em>; and that one
of the halves thus obtained must be 
added to the coefficient on the Variable which precedes it by ten 
columns, and the other half to the coefficient on the Variable which 
precedes it by twelve columns; V<sub>32</sub>, V<sub>33</sub>, &amp;c. themselves becoming zeros 
during the process.
</p>

<p>

This series of operations may be thus expressed:&mdash;
</p>

<map name="notee3" id="notee3">
<area shape="rect" coords="610,67,633,101" href="sketch_foot.html#note18" alt="Footnote 18" />
</map>
<center>
<em>
Fourth Series
</em>
<br />
<a class="i" name="BKnote18" href="sketch_foot.html#note18">
<img src="figures/notee3.png" usemap="#notee3" border="0" width="633" height="187" alt="" />
</a>
<br />
<font size="-1" face="Helvetica"><a href="sketch_foot.html#note18">Read footnote</a></font>.
</center>

<p>

The calculation of the coefficients C<sub>0</sub>, C<sub>1</sub>, &amp;c. of (1.) would now be 
completed, and they would stand ranged in order on V<sub>20</sub>, V<sub>21</sub>, &amp;c. It will 
be remarked, that from the moment the fourth series of operations is 
ordered, the Variables V<sub>31</sub>, V<sub>32</sub>, &amp;c. cease to be <em>Result</em>-Variables, and 
become mere <em>Working</em>-Variables.
</p>

<p>

The substitution made by the engine of the processes in the second side of 
(3.) for those in the first side is an excellent illustration of the manner in 
which we may arbitrarily order it to substitute any function, number, or 
process, at pleasure, for any other function, number or process, on the 
occurrence of a specified contingency.
</p>

<p>

We will now suppose that we desire to go a step further, and to obtain
the numerical value of each <em>complete</em> term of the product
(1.); that is, of each <em>coefficient and variable united</em>, which
for the (<em>n</em> + 1)th term would be <img src="figures/adaeq21.png" align="bottom" width="80" height="14" alt="${\rm C}_n\cdot\cos n\theta$" />.
</p>

<p>

We must for this purpose place the variables themselves on another set of 
columns, V<sub>41</sub>, V<sub>42</sub>, &amp;c., and then order their successive multiplication by 
V<sub>21</sub>, V<sub>22</sub>, &amp;c., each for each. There would thus be a final series of 
operations as follows:&mdash;
</p>

<center>
<table>
<tr>
<td align="center"><em>Fifth and Final Series of Operations</em></td>
</tr>
<tr>
    <td align="center"><sup>2</sup>V<sub>20</sub> &times; <sup>0</sup>V<sub>40</sub>&nbsp;=&nbsp;<sup>1</sup>V<sub>40</sub></td>
</tr>

<tr>
    <td align="center"><sup>3</sup>V<sub>21</sub> &times; <sup>0</sup>V<sub>41</sub>&nbsp;=&nbsp;<sup>1</sup>V<sub>41</sub></td>
</tr>

<tr>
    <td align="center"><sup>3</sup>V<sub>22</sub> &times; <sup>0</sup>V<sub>42</sub>&nbsp;=&nbsp;<sup>1</sup>V<sub>42</sub></td>
</tr>

<tr>
    <td align="center"><sup>2</sup>V<sub>23</sub> &times; <sup>0</sup>V<sub>43</sub>&nbsp;=&nbsp;<sup>1</sup>V<sub>43</sub></td>
</tr>

<tr>
    <td align="center"><sup>1</sup>V<sub>24</sub> &times; <sup>0</sup>V<sub>44</sub>&nbsp;=&nbsp;<sup>1</sup>V<sub>44</sub></td>
</tr>
</table>
</center>

<p>

(N.B. that V<sub>40</sub> being intended to receive the coefficient on V<sub>20</sub> which has 
<em>no</em> variable, will only have cos 0<em>&theta;</em>
(=1) inscribed on it, preparatory to 
commencing the fifth series of operations.)
</p>

<p>

From the moment that the fifth and final series of operations is ordered, 
the Variables V<sub>20</sub>, V<sub>21</sub>, &amp;c. then in their turn
cease to be <em>Result</em>-Variables and become mere
<em>Working</em>-Variables; V<sub>40</sub>, V<sub>41</sub>, &amp;c. being 
now the recipients of the ultimate results.
</p>

<p>

We should observe, that if the variables cos&nbsp;<em>&theta;</em>,
cos&nbsp;2<em>&theta;</em>,
cos&nbsp;3<em>&theta;</em>, &amp;c. are 
furnished, they would be placed directly upon V<sub>41</sub>, V<sub>42</sub>, &amp;c., like any 
other data. If not, a separate computation might be entered upon in a 
separate part of the engine, in order to calculate them, and place them on 
V<sub>41</sub>, &amp;c.
</p>

<p>

We have now explained how the engine might compute (1.) in the most 
direct manner, supposing we knew nothing about the <em>general</em> term of the 
resulting series. But the engine would in reality set to work very 
differently, whenever (as in this case) we <em>do</em> know the law for the general 
term.
</p>

<p>

The first two terms of (1.) are
</p>

<table>
<tr>
<td align="center" width="99%"><img src="figures/adaeq8.png" width="461" height="31" 
    alt="({\rm B}{\rm A}+\frac{1}{2}\BB{1}\ZA{1})+(\overline{{\rm B}\ZA{1}+\BB{1}{\rm A}+\frac{1}{2}\BB{1}\ZA{2}}\cdot\cos\theta)"/></td>
<td align="right" width="1%">(4.)</td>
</tr>
</table>

<p>

and the general term for all after these is
</p>

<table>
<tr>
<td align="center" width="99%"><img src="figures/adaeq9.png" width="340" height="28"
    alt="({\rm B}{\rm A}_n+\frac{1}{2}\BB{1}\cdot\overline{\ZA{n-1}+\ZA{n+2}})\cos n\theta" /></td>
<td align="right" width="1%">(5.)</td>
</tr>
</table>

<p>

which is the coefficient of the (<em>n</em>+1)th term.
The engine would calculate the first two terms by means of
a separate set of suitable Operation-cards, and would then
need another set for the third term; which last set of 
Operation-cards would calculate all the succeeding terms <em>ad infinitum</em>, 
merely requiring certain new Variable-cards for each term to direct the 
operations to act on the proper columns. The following would be the 
successive sets of operations for computing the coefficients of <em>n</em>+2 
terms:&mdash;
</p>

<center>
(&times;, &times;, &divide;, +), (&times;, &times;, &times;, &divide;, +, +),
    <em>n</em>(&times;, +, &times;, &divide;, +).
</center>

<p>
Or we might represent them as follows, according to the numerical order 
of the operations:&mdash;
</p>


<center>
(1, 2&hellip;4), (5, 6&hellip;10), <em>n</em>(11, 12&hellip;15).
</center>

<p>

The brackets, it should be understood, point out the relation in which the 
operations may be <em>grouped</em>, while the comma marks <em>succession</em>. The 
symbol + might be used for this latter purpose, but this would be liable to 
produce confusion, as + is also necessarily used to represent one class of 
the actual operations which are the subject of that succession. In 
accordance with this meaning attached to the comma, care must be taken 
when any one group of operations recurs more than once, as is represented 
above by <em>n</em>(11&hellip;l5), not to insert a comma after the number or letter 
prefixed to that group.  <em>n</em>, (11&hellip;15) would stand for <em>an operation n, 
followed by the group of operations</em> (11&hellip;15); instead of denoting <em>the 
number of groups which are to follow each other</em>.
</p>

<p>

Wherever a <em>general</em> term exists, there will be a <em>recurring group</em> of 
operations, as in the above example. Both for brevity and for distinctness, 
a <em>recurring group</em> is called a <em>cycle</em>. A <em>cycle</em> of operations, then, must be 
understood to signify any <em>set of operations</em> which is repeated <em>more than 
once</em>. It is equally a <em>cycle</em>, whether it be repeated <em>twice</em> only, or an 
indefinite number of times; for it is the fact of a <em>repetition occurring at all</em>
that constitutes it such. In many cases of analysis there is a <em>recurring 
group</em> of one or more <em>cycles</em>; that is, a <em>cycle of a cycle</em>,
or a <em>cycle of cycles</em>. 
For instance: suppose we wish to divide a series by a series,
</p>

<table>
<tr>
<td align="right" width="1%">(1.)</td>
<td align="center" width="99%"><img src="figures/adaeq10.png" width="133" height="33"
    alt="\frac{a+bx+cx^2+\ldots}{a'+b'x+c'x^2+\ldots}," /></td>
</tr>
</table>

<p>

it being required that the result shall be developed, like the dividend and 
the divisor, in successive powers of <em>x</em>. A little consideration of (1.), and of 
the steps through which algebraical division is effected, will show that (if 
the denominator be supposed to consist of <em>p</em> terms) the first partial quotient 
will be completed by the following operations:&mdash;
</p>

<table>
<tr>
<td align="right" width="1%">(2.)</td>
<td align="center" width="99%">{(&divide;), <em>p</em>(&times;, &minus;)} &nbsp;&nbsp;or&nbsp;&nbsp; {(1), <em>p</em>(2, 3)},</td>
</tr>
</table>

<p>

that the second partial quotient will be 
completed by an exactly similar set of operations, which acts on the 
remainder obtained by the first set, instead of on the original dividend. 
The whole of the processes therefore that have been gone through, by the 
time the <em>second</em> partial quotient has been obtained, will be,&mdash;
</p>

<table>
<tr>
<td align="right" width="1%">(3.)</td>
<td align="center" width="99%">2{(&divide;), <em>p</em>( &times; , &minus;)} &nbsp;&nbsp;or&nbsp;&nbsp; 2{(1), <em>p</em>(2, 3)},</td>
</tr>
</table>

<p>

which is a cycle that includes a cycle, or a cycle of the second order. The 
operations for the <em>complete</em> division, supposing we propose to obtain <em>n</em> 
terms of the series constituting the quotient, will be,&mdash;
</p>

<table>
<tr>
<td align="right" width="1%">(4.)</td>
<td align="center" width="99%"><em>n</em>{(&divide;), <em>p</em>( &times; , &minus;)} &nbsp;&nbsp;or&nbsp;&nbsp; <em>n</em>{(1), <em>p</em>(2, 3)},</td>
</tr>
</table>

<p>

It is of course to be remembered that the process of algebraical division in 
reality continues <em>ad infinitum</em>, except in the few exceptional cases
which admit of an exact quotient being obtained. The number <em>n</em> in the 
formula (4.) is always that of the number of terms we propose to ourselves 
to obtain; and the <em>n</em>th partial quotient is the coefficient of the (<em>n</em>-1)th 
power of <em>x</em>.
</p>

<p>

There are some cases which entail <em>cycles of cycles of cycles</em>, to an 
indefinite extent. Such cases are usually very complicated, and they are of 
extreme interest when considered with reference to the engine. The 
algebraical development in a series of the <em>n</em>th function of any given 
function is of this nature. Let it be proposed to obtain the <em>n</em>th
function of
</p>

<table>
<tr>
<td align="right" width="1%">(5.)</td>
<td align="center" width="99%">&Phi;(<em>a</em>, <em>b</em>, <em>c</em>, &hellip;, <em>x</em>), <em>x</em> being the variable.</td>
</tr>
</table>

<p>

We should premise, that we suppose the reader to understand what is 
meant by an <em>n</em>th function. We suppose him likewise to comprehend 
distinctly the difference between developing
<em>an n</em>th <em>function algebraically</em>, 
and merely <em>calculating an n</em>th <em>function arithmetically</em>.
If he does not, the 
following will be by no means very intelligible; but we have not space to 
give any preliminary explanations. To proceed: the law, according to 
which the successive functions of (5.) are to be developed, must of course 
first be fixed on. This law may be of very various kinds. We may propose 
to obtain our results in successive <em>powers</em> of <em>x</em>,
in which case the general 
form would be
</p>

<center>
C + C<sub>1</sub><em>x</em> + C<sub>2</sub><em>x</em><sup>2</sup> + &amp;c.;
</center>

<p>

or in successive powers of <em>n</em> itself, the index of the function we are 
ultimately to obtain, in which case the general form would be
</p>

<center>
C + C<sub>1</sub><em>n</em> + C<sub>2</sub><em>n</em><sup>2</sup> + &amp;c.;
</center>

<p>

and <em>x</em> would only enter in the coefficients. Again, other functions of <em>x</em> or 
of <em>n</em> instead of <em>powers</em> might be selected. It might be in addition proposed, 
that the coefficients themselves should be arranged according to given 
functions of a certain quantity. Another mode would be to make equations 
arbitrarily amongst the coefficients only, in which case the several 
functions, according to either of which it might be possible to develope the 
<em>n</em>th function of (5.), would have to be determined from the combined 
consideration of these equations and of (5.) itself.
</p>

<p>

The <em>algebraical</em> nature of the engine (so strongly insisted on in a previous 
part of this Note) would enable it to follow out any of these various modes 
indifferently; just as we recently showed that it can distribute and separate 
the numerical results of any one prescribed series of processes, in a 
perfectly arbitrary manner. Were it otherwise, the engine could merely 
<em>compute the arithmetical n</em>th <em>function</em>,
a result which, like any other purely 
arithmetical results, would be simply a collective
number, bearing no traces of the data or the processes which had led to it.
</p>

<p>

Secondly, the <em>law</em> of development for the <em>n</em>th function being selected, the 
next step would obviously be to develope (5.) itself, according to this law. 
This result would be the first function, and would be obtained by a 
determinate series of processes. These in most cases would include 
amongst them one or more <em>cycles</em> of operations.
</p>

<p>

The third step (which would consist of the various processes necessary for 
effecting the actual substitution of the series constituting the <em>first function</em>, 
for the <em>variable</em> itself) might proceed in either of two ways. It might make 
the substitution either wherever <em>x</em> occurs in the original (5.), or it might 
similarly make it wherever <em>x</em> occurs in the first function itself which is the 
equivalent of (5.). In some cases the former mode might be best, and in 
others the latter.
</p>

<p>

Whichever is adopted, it must be understood that the result is to appear 
arranged in a series following the law originally prescribed for the 
development of the <em>n</em>th function. This result constitutes the second 
function; with which we are to proceed exactly as we did with the first 
function, in order to obtain the third function, and so on, <em>n</em>-1 times, to 
obtain the <em>n</em>th function. We easily perceive that since every successive 
function is arranged in a series <em>following the same law</em>, there would (after 
the <em>first</em> function is obtained) be a <a name="BKnote19" href="sketch_foot.html#note19"><em>cycle of a cycle of a cycle</em>, &amp;c. of 
operations</a>, one, two, three, up to <em>n</em>-1 times, in order to get the  <em>n</em>th 
function. We say, <em>after the first function is obtained</em>, because (for reasons 
on which we cannot here enter) the <em>first</em> function might in many cases be 
developed through a set of processes peculiar to itself, and not recurring 
for the remaining functions.
</p>

<p>

We have given but a very slight sketch of the principal <em>general</em> steps 
which would be requisite for obtaining an <em>n</em>th function of such a formula 
as (5.). The question is so exceedingly complicated, that perhaps few 
persons can be expected to follow, to their own satisfaction, so brief and 
general a statement as we are here restricted to on this subject. Still it is a 
very important case as regards the engine, and suggests ideas peculiar to 
itself, which we should regret to pass wholly without allusion. Nothing 
could be more interesting than to follow out, in every detail, the solution 
by the engine of such a case as the
above; but the time, space and labour this would necessitate, could only 
suit a very extensive work.
</p>

<p>

To return to the subject of <em>cycles</em> of operations: some of the notation of 
the integral calculus lends itself very aptly to express them: (2.) might be 
thus written:&mdash;
</p>

<table>
<tr>
<td align="right" width="1%">(6.)</td>
<td align="center" width="99%"><img src="figures/adaeq11.png" width="423" height="23"
    alt="$(\div ),\sum (+1)^p(\times,-)$\hspace{1em}or\hspace{1em}$(1),\sum(+1)^p(2,3)$," /></td>
</tr>
</table>

<p>

where <em>p</em> stands for the 
variable; (+ 1)<sup><em>p</em></sup> for the function of the variable, that is, 
for &Phi;<em>p</em>; and the 
limits are from 1 to <em>p</em>, or from 0 to <em>p</em>-1, each increment being equal to 
unity. Similarly, (4.) would be,&mdash;
</p>

<table>
<tr>
<td align="right" width="1%">(7.)</td>
<td align="center" width="99%"><img src="figures/adaeq12.png" width="287" height="23"
    alt="\sum (+1)^n\{(\div ),\sum (+1)^p(\times,-)\}" /></td>
</tr>
</table>

<p>

the limits of n being from 
1 to <em>n</em>, or from 0 to <em>n</em>-1,
</p>

<table>
<tr>
<td align="right" width="1%">(8.)</td>
<td align="center" width="99%">or&nbsp;&nbsp; <img src="figures/adaeq13.png" align="middle" width="274" height="23"
    alt="\sum (+1)^n\{(1),\sum (+1)^p(2,3)\}" /></td>
</tr>
</table>

<p>

Perhaps it may be thought that this notation is merely a circuitous way of 
expressing what was more simply and as effectually expressed before; 
and, in the above example, there may be some truth in this. But there is 
another description of cycles which <em>can</em> only effectually be expressed, in a 
condensed form, by the preceding notation. We shall call them <em>varying 
cycles</em>. They are of frequent occurrence, and include successive cycles of 
operations of the following nature:&mdash;
</p>

<table>
<tr>
<td align="right" width="1%">(9.)</td>
<td align="center" width="99%"><img src="figures/adaeq14.png" width="643" height="24"
    alt="p(1,2\ldots m),\overline{p-1}(1,2\ldots m),\overline{p-2}(1,2\ldots m)\ldots\overline{p-n}(1,2\ldots m)" /></td>
</tr>
</table>

<p>

where each cycle contains the same group of operations, but in which the 
number of repetitions of the group varies according to a fixed rate, with 
every cycle. (9.) can be well expressed as follows:&mdash;
</p>

<table>
<tr>
<td align="right" width="1%">(10.)</td>
<td align="center" width="99%"><img src="figures/adaeq15.png" align="middle" width="138" height="23"
    alt="\sum p(1,2\ldots m)" />, the limits of <em>p</em> being from <em>p</em>-<em>n</em> to <em>p</em>.</td>
</tr>
</table>

<p>

Independent of the intrinsic advantages which we thus perceive to result in 
certain cases from this use of the notation of the integral calculus, there are 
likewise considerations which make it interesting, from the connections 
and relations involved in this new application. It has been observed in 
some of the former Notes, that the processes used in analysis form a 
logical system of much higher generality than the applications to number 
merely. Thus, when we read over any algebraical formula, considering it 
exclusively with reference to the processes of the engine, and putting aside 
for the moment its abstract signification as to the relations of quantity, the 
symbols +, &times;, &amp;c. in reality represent (as their immediate and proximate 
effect, when the formula is applied to the engine) that a certain prism 
which is a part of the mechanism (see <a href="#NoteC">Note C</a>.)
turns a new face, and thus 
presents a new card to act on the bundles of levers of the engine; the new 
card being perforated with holes, which are arranged according to the
peculiarities of the operation of addition, or of multiplication, &amp;c. Again, 
the <em>numbers</em> in the preceding formula (8.), each of them really represents 
one of these very pieces of card that are hung over the prism.
</p>

<p>

Now in the use made in the formul&aelig; (7.), (8.) and (10.), of the notation of 
the integral calculus, we have glimpses of a similar new application of the 
language of the <em>higher</em> mathematics.
&Sigma;, in reality, here indicates that when 
a certain number of cards have acted in succession, the prism over which 
they revolve must <em>rotate backwards</em>, so as to bring those cards into their 
former position; and the limits 1 to <em>n</em>, 1 to <em>p</em>, &amp;c., regulate how often this 
backward rotation is to be repeated.
</p>

<p class="r">
A. A. L.
</p>

<center>
<h3><em><a name="NoteF" class="f">Note F</a></em></h3>
</center>

<p>
There is in existence a beautiful woven portrait of Jacquard, in the 
fabrication of which 24,000 cards were required.
</p>

<p>

The power of <em>repeating</em> the cards, <a href="#menaref2">alluded to</a> by M. Menabrea, 
and more fully explained in <a href="#NoteC">Note C</a>.,
reduces to an immense extent the 
number of cards required. It is obvious that this mechanical improvement 
is especially applicable wherever <em>cycles</em> occur in the mathematical 
operations, and that, in preparing data for calculations by the engine, it is 
desirable to arrange the order and combination of the processes with a 
view to obtain them as much as possible <em>symmetrically</em> and in cycles, in 
order that the mechanical advantages of the <em>backing</em> system may be 
applied to the utmost. It is here interesting to observe the manner in which 
the value of an <em>analytical</em> resource is <em>met</em> and <em>enhanced</em> by an ingenious 
<em>mechanical</em> contrivance. We see in it an instance of one of those mutual 
<em>adjustments</em> between the purely mathematical and the mechanical 
departments, mentioned in <a href="#NoteA">Note A</a>. as being a main and essential condition 
of success in the invention of a calculating engine. The nature of the 
resources afforded by such adjustments would be of two principal kinds. 
In some cases, a difficulty (perhaps in itself insurmountable) in the one 
department would be overcome by facilities in the other; and sometimes 
(as in the present case) a strong point in the one would be rendered still 
stronger and more available by combination with a corresponding strong 
point in the other.
</p>

<p>

As a mere example of the degree to which the combined systems of cycles 
and of backing can diminish the <em>number</em> of cards requisite, we
shall choose a case which places it in strong evidence, and which has
likewise the advantage of being a perfectly different <em>kind</em>
of problem from those that are mentioned in any of the other Notes.
Suppose it be required to eliminate nine variables from ten
simple equations of the form&mdash;
</p>

<table>
<tr>
<td align="right" width="50%"><em>ax</em><sub>0</sub> + <em>bx</em><sub>1</sub> + <em>cx</em><sub>2</sub> + <em>dx</em><sub>3</sub> + &middot;&middot;&middot;</td>
<td align="left"  width="49%">= <em>p</em></td>
<td align="right" width="1%">(1.)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="right" width="50%"><em>a</em><sup>1</sup><em>x</em><sub>0</sub> + <em>b</em><sup>1</sup><em>x</em><sub>1</sub> + <em>c</em><sup>1</sup><em>x</em><sub>2</sub> + <em>d</em><sup>1</sup><em>x</em><sub>3</sub> + &middot;&middot;&middot;</td>
<td align="left"  width="49%">= <em>p'</em></td>
<td align="right" width="1%">(2.)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="right" width="50%">&amp;c.&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&amp;c.&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&amp;c.&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;</td>
<td align="left"  width="49%">&amp;c.</td>
<td align="right" width="1%">&nbsp;</td>
</tr>
</table>

<p>

We should explain, before proceeding, that it is not our object to consider 
this problem with reference to the actual arrangement of the data on the 
Variables of the engine, but simply as an abstract question of the <em>nature</em> and 
<em>number</em> of the <em>operations</em> required to be performed during its complete 
solution.
</p>

<p>

The first step would be the elimination of the first unknown quantity
<em>x</em><sub>0</sub> between the first two equations.
This would be obtained by the form&mdash;
</p>

<center>
(<em>a</em><sup>1</sup><em>a</em>-<em>a</em><em>a</em><sup>1</sup>)<em>x</em><sub>0</sub> + (<em>a</em><sup>1</sup><em>b</em>-<em>a</em><em>b</em><sup>1</sup>)<em>x</em><sub>1</sub> + (<em>a</em><sup>1</sup><em>c</em>-<em>a</em><em>c</em><sup>1</sup>)<em>x</em><sub>2</sub> +<br />
+ (<em>a</em><sup>1</sup><em>d</em>-<em>a</em><em>d</em><sup>1</sup>)<em>x</em><sub>3</sub> + &middot; &middot; &middot; &middot; &middot; &middot; &middot; &middot; &middot; &middot; &middot; &middot; &middot; &middot; &middot; &middot; &middot; &middot; &middot; &middot; &middot; &middot; &middot; &middot; = <em>a</em><sup>1</sup><em>p</em>-<em>a</em><em>p</em><sup>1</sup>,
</center>

<p>

for which the operations 10 (&times;, &times;, &minus;) would be needed. The second step 
would be the elimination of <em>x</em><sub>0</sub> between
the second and third equations, for 
which the operations would be precisely the same. We should then have 
had altogether the following operations:&mdash;
</p>

<center>
    10(&times;, &times;, &minus;), 10(&times;, &times;, &minus;) = 20(&times;, &times;, &minus;)
</center>

<p>

Continuing in the same manner, the total number of operations for the 
complete elimination of <em>x</em><sub>0</sub> between all the successive pairs of equations 
would be&mdash;
</p>


<center>
    9 &middot; 10(&times;, &times;, &minus;) = 90(&times;, &times;, &minus;)
</center>

<p>

We should then be left with nine simple equations of nine variables from
which to eliminate the next variable <em>x</em><sub>1</sub>, for
which the total of the processes 
would be
</p>


<center>
    8 &middot; 9(&times;, &times;, &minus;) = 72(&times;, &times;, &minus;)
</center>

<p>

We should then be left with eight simple equations of eight variables from
which to eliminate <em>x</em><sub>2</sub>, for which the processes would be&mdash;
</p>


<center>
    7 &middot; 8(&times;, &times;, &minus;) = 56(&times;, &times;, &minus;)
</center>

<p>

and so on. The total operations for the elimination of all the variables would 
thus be&mdash;
</p>

<center>
    9&middot;10 + 8&middot;9 + 7&middot;8 + 6&middot;7 + 5&middot;6 + 4&middot;5 + 3&middot;4 + 2&middot;3 + 1&middot;2 = 330.
</center>
<p>

So that <em>three</em> Operation-cards would perform the office of 330 such cards.
</p>

<p>

If we take <em>n</em> simple equations containing <em>n</em>&minus;1 variables,
<em>n</em> being a number 
unlimited in magnitude, the case becomes still more obvious, as the same 
three cards might then take the place of thousands or millions
of cards.
</p>

<p>

We shall now draw further attention to the fact, already noticed, of its being 
by no means necessary that a formula proposed for solution should ever have 
been actually worked out, as a condition for enabling the engine to solve it. 
Provided we know the <em>series of operations</em> to be gone through, that is 
sufficient. In the foregoing instance this will be 
obvious enough on a slight consideration.
And it is a circumstance 
which deserves particular notice, since herein may reside a latent value of 
such an engine almost incalculable in its possible ultimate results. We 
already know that there are functions whose numerical value it is
of importance for the purposes both of abstract and of practical science to 
ascertain, but whose determination requires processes so lengthy and so 
complicated, that, although it is possible to arrive at them through great 
expenditure of time, labour and money, it is yet on these accounts 
practically almost unattainable; and we can conceive there being some 
results which it may be <em>absolutely impossible</em> in practice to attain with any 
accuracy, and whose precise determination it may prove highly important for
some of the future wants of science, in its manifold, complicated and
rapidly-developing fields of inquiry, to arrive at.
</p>

<p>

Without, however, stepping into the region of conjecture, we will mention a 
particular problem which occurs to us at this moment as being an apt 
illustration of the use to which such an engine may be turned for
determining that which human brains find it difficult or impossible to work 
out unerringly. In the solution of the famous problem of the Three Bodies,
there are, out of about 295 coefficients of lunar perturbations given by M. 
Clausen (Astro<sup>e</sup>. Nachrichten, No. 406) as the result of the calculations by 
Burg, of two by Damoiseau, and of one by Burckhardt, fourteen coefficients 
that differ in the nature of their algebraic sign; and out of the remainder there 
are only 101 (or about one-third) that agree precisely both in signs and in 
amount. These discordances, which are generally small in individual 
magnitude, may arise either from an erroneous determination of the abstract 
coefficients in the development of the problem, or from discrepancies in the 
data deduced from observation, or from both causes combined. The former 
is the most ordinary source of error in astronomical computations, and this 
the engine would entirely obviate.
</p>

<p>

We might even invent laws for series or formul&aelig; in an arbitrary manner, and 
set the engine to work upon them, and thus deduce numerical results which 
we might not otherwise have thought of obtaining; but this would hardly 
perhaps in any instance be productive of any great practical utility, or 
calculated to rank higher than as a philosophical amusement.
</p>

<p class="r">
A. A. L.
</p>

<center>
<h3><em><a name="NoteG" class="f">Note G</a></em></h3>
</center>

<p>
It is desirable to guard against the possibility of exaggerated ideas that 
might arise as to the powers of the Analytical Engine. In considering any 
new subject, there is frequently a tendency, first, to <em>overrate</em> what we find 
to be already interesting or remarkable; and, secondly, by a sort of natural 
reaction, to <em>undervalue</em> the true state of the case, when we do discover that 
our notions have surpassed those that were really tenable.
</p>

<p>

The Analytical Engine has no pretensions whatever to <em>originate</em> anything. 
It can do whatever we <em>know how to order it</em> to perform. It can <em>follow</em> 
analysis; but it has no power of <em>anticipating</em> any analytical relations or 
truths. Its province is to assist us in making <em>available</em> what we are already 
acquainted with. This it is calculated to effect primarily and chiefly of 
course, through its executive faculties; but it is likely to exert an <em>indirect</em>
and reciprocal influence on science itself in another manner. For, in so 
distributing and combining the truths and the formul&aelig; of analysis, that they 
may become most easily and rapidly amenable to the mechanical 
combinations of the engine, the relations and the nature of many subjects 
in that science are necessarily thrown into new lights, and more profoundly 
investigated. This is a decidedly indirect, and a somewhat <em>speculative</em>, 
consequence of such an invention. It is however pretty evident, on general 
principles, that in devising for mathematical truths a new form in which to 
record and throw themselves out for actual use, views are likely to be 
induced, which should again react on the more theoretical phase of the 
subject. There are in all extensions of human power, or additions to human 
knowledge, various <em>collateral</em> influences, besides the main and primary 
object attained.
</p>

<p>

To return to the executive faculties of this engine: the question must arise 
in every mind, are they <em>really</em> even able to <em>follow</em> analysis in its whole 
extent? No reply, entirely satisfactory to all minds, can be given to this 
query, excepting the actual existence of the engine, and actual experience 
of its practical results. We will however sum up for each reader's 
consideration the chief elements with which the engine works:&mdash;
</p>

<ol>
<li>It performs the four operations of simple arithmetic upon any numbers 
whatever.</li>

<li>By means of certain artifices and arrangements (upon which we cannot 
enter within the restricted space which such a publication as the present 
may admit of), there is no limit either to the <em>magnitude</em> of the <em>numbers</em>
used, or to the <em>number of quantities</em> (either variables or constants) that 
may be employed.</li>

<li>It can combine these numbers and these quantities either algebraically 
or arithmetically, in relations unlimited as to variety, extent, or complexity.</li>

<li>It uses algebraic <em>signs</em> according to their proper laws, and developes the 
logical consequences of these laws.</li>

<li>It can arbitrarily substitute any formula for any other; effacing the first 
from the columns on which it is represented, and making the second 
appear in its stead.</li>

<li>It can provide for singular values. Its power of doing this is referred to 
in M. Menabrea's memoir, <a href="#menaref6">where he mentions</a> the passage of 
values through zero and infinity. The practicability of causing it arbitrarily 
to change its processes at any moment, on the occurrence of any specified 
contingency (of which its substitution of
<img src="figures/adaeq19.png" align="bottom" width="215" height="22"
    alt="(\frac{1}{2}\cos\overline{n+1}\theta+\frac{1}{2}\cos\overline{n-1}\theta)" />
for <img src="figures/adaeq20.png" align="bottom" width="104" height="17"
    alt="(\cos n\theta\cdot\cos\theta)" />, explained in <a href="#NoteE">Note E</a>.,
is in 
some degree an illustration), at once secures this point.</li>
</ol>

<p>
The subject of integration and of differentiation demands some notice. The 
engine can effect these processes in either of two ways:&mdash;
</p>

<p>
First. We may order it, by means of the Operation and of the
Variable-cards, to go through the various steps by which the
required <em>limit</em> can be 
worked out for whatever function is under consideration.
</p>

<p>
Secondly. It may (if we know the form of the limit for the function in 
question) effect the <a name="BKnote20" href="sketch_foot.html#note20">integration or differentiation by direct</a> substitution. 
We remarked in <a href="#NoteB">Note B</a>., that any <em>set</em> of columns on which numbers are 
inscribed, represents merely a <em>general</em> function of the several quantities, 
until the special function have been impressed by means of the Operation 
and Variable-cards. Consequently, if instead of requiring the value of the 
function, we require that of its integral, or of its differential coefficient, we 
have merely to order whatever particular combination of the ingredient 
quantities may constitute
that integral or that coefficient. In <em>ax<sup>n</sup></em>, for instance, instead of the 
quantities
</p>

<center>
<img src="figures/notegn4.png" width="244" height="98" alt="" />
</center>

<p>

being ordered to appear on V<sub>3</sub> in the combination
<em>ax<sup>n</sup></em>, they would be 
ordered to appear in that of
</p>

<center>
<em>anx</em><sup><em>n</em>-1</sup>
</center>
<p>

They would then stand thus:&mdash;
</p>

<center>
<img src="figures/notegn3.png" width="281" height="104" alt="" />
</center>

<p>

Similarly, we might have <img src="figures/adaeq23.png" align="middle" width="69" height="22" alt="(a/(n+1))*x^(n+1)" />,
the integral of <em>ax<sup>n</sup></em>.
</p>

<p>

An interesting example for following out the processes of the engine 
would be such a form as
</p>

<center>
<img src="figures/notegn2.png" width="131" height="57"
    alt="\int{\frac{x^n\, dx}{\sqrt{a^2-x^2}}}\raisebox{2pt}{{\rm ,}}"/>
</center>

<p>

or any other cases of integration by successive reductions, where an 
integral which contains an operation repeated <em>n</em> times can be made to 
depend upon another which contains the same <em>n</em>-1 or <em>n</em>-2 times, and so 
on until by continued reduction we arrive at a certain <em>ultimate</em> form, whose 
value has then to be determined.
</p>

<p>

The methods in Arbogast's <em lang="fr" xml:lang="fr">Calcul des D&eacute;rivations</em> are peculiarly fitted for 
the notation and the processes of the engine. Likewise the whole of the 
Combinatorial Analysis, which consists first in a purely numerical 
calculation of indices, and secondly in the distribution and combination of 
the quantities according to laws prescribed by these indices.
</p>

<p>

We will terminate these Notes by following up in detail the steps through 
which the engine could compute the Numbers of Bernoulli, this being (in 
the form in which we shall deduce it) a rather complicated example of its 
powers. The simplest manner of computing these
numbers would be from the direct expansion 
of
</p>

<table>
<tr>
<td align="center" width="99%"><img src="figures/notege1.png" width="354" height="62"
    alt="\frac{x}{\epsilon^x-1}=\frac{1}{1+\frac{x}{2}+\frac{x^2}{2\cdot 3}+\frac{x^3}{2\cdot 3\cdot 4}+{\rm \ETC}}" /></td>
<td align="right" width="1%">(1.)</td>
</tr>
</table>

<p>

which is in fact a particular case of the development 
of
</p>

<center>
<img src="figures/notege1a.png" width="215" height="56"
    alt="\frac{a+bx+cx^2+\RMETC}{a'+b'x+c'x^2+\RMETC}" />
</center>

<p>

mentioned in <a href="#NoteE">Note E</a>. 
Or again, we might compute them from the
well-known form
</p>

<table>
<tr>
<td align="center" width="99%"><img src="figures/notege2.png" width="517" height="57"
    alt="{\rm B}_{2n-1}=2\cdot\frac{1\cdot 2\cdot 3\ldots 2n}{(2\pi )^{2n}}\cdot\left\{1+\frac{1}{2^{2n}}+\frac{1}{3^{2n}}+\cdots\right\}" /></td>
<td align="right" width="1%">(2.)</td>
</tr>
</table>

<p>

or from the form
</p>

<table>
<tr>
<!-- ./textogif -dpi 129 notege3 -->
<td align="center" width="99%"><img src="figures/notege3.png" width="639" height="175" alt="" /></td>
<td align="right" width="1%">(3.)</td>
</tr>
</table>

<p>

or from many others. As however our object is not simplicity or facility of 
computation, but the illustration of the powers of the engine, we prefer 
selecting the formula below, marked (8.) This is derived in the following 
manner:&mdash;
</p>

<p>

If in the equation
</p>

<table>
<tr>
<td align="center" width="99%"><img src="figures/notege4.png" width="636" height="55"
    alt="\frac{x}{\epsilon^x-1}=1-\frac{x}{2}+\BB{1}\frac{x^2}{2}+\BB{3}\frac{x^4}{2\cdot 3 \cdot 4} + \BB{5}\frac{x^6}{2\cdot 3 \cdot 4 \cdot 5 \cdot 6}+\cdots" /></td>
<td align="right" width="1%">(4.)</td>
</tr>
</table>

<p>

(in which B<sub>1</sub>, B<sub>3</sub>&hellip;, &amp;c. are the Numbers of Bernoulli), we expand the 
denominator of the first side in powers of <em>x</em>, and then divide both 
numerator and denominator by <em>x</em>, we shall derive
</p>

<table>
<tr>
<!-- ./textogif -dpi 128 notege5 -->
<td align="center" width="99%"><img src="figures/notege5.png" width="645" height="53"
    alt="1=\left(1-\frac{x}{2}+\BB{1}\frac{x^2}{2}+\BB{3}\frac{x^4}{2\cdot 3\cdot 4}+\cdots\right)\left(1+\frac{x}{2}+\frac{x^2}{2\cdot 3}+\frac{x^3}{2\cdot 3\cdot 4}+\cdots\right)" /></td>
<td align="right" width="1%">(5.)</td>
</tr>
</table>

<p>

If this latter multiplication be actually performed, we shall have a series of 
the general form
</p>

<table>
<tr>
<td align="center" width="99%"><img src="figures/notege6.png" width="307" height="25"
    alt="1+\DD{1}x+\DD{2}x^2+\DD{3}x^3+\cdots" /></td>
<td align="right" width="1%">(6.)</td>
</tr>
</table>

<p>

in which we see, first, that all the coefficients of the powers of <em>x</em> are 
severally equal to zero; and secondly, that the general form for D<sub>2<em>n</em></sub>, the 
coefficient of the 2<em>n</em>+1th <em>term</em>
(that is of <em>x</em><sup>2<em>n</em></sup> any <em>even</em>
power of <em>x</em>), is the 
following:&mdash;
</p>

<table>
<tr>
<td align="center" width="99%"><img src="figures/notege7.png" width="583" height="75" alt="" /></td>
<td align="right" width="1%">(7.)</td>
</tr>
</table>

<p>

Multiplying every term by (2&middot;3&hellip;2<em>n</em>) we have
</p>

<table>
<tr>
<td align="center" width="99%"><img src="figures/notege8.png" width="535" height="75" alt="" /></td>
<td align="right" width="1%">(8.)</td>
</tr>
</table>

<p>

which it may be convenient to write under the general form:&mdash;
</p>

<table>
<tr>
<td align="center" width="99%"><img src="figures/notege9.png" width="480" height="24"
    alt="0=\ZA{0}+\ZA{1}\BB{1}+\ZA{3}\BB{3}+\ZA{5}\BB{5}+\cdots +\BB{2n-1}" /></td>
<td align="right" width="1%">(9.)</td>
</tr>
</table>

<p>
 

A<sub>1</sub>, A<sub>3</sub>, &amp;c. being those functions of <em>n</em> which respectively belong to 
B<sub>1</sub>, B<sub>3</sub>, &amp;c.
</p>

<p>

We might have derived a form nearly similar to (8.), from D<sub>2<em>n</em>-1</sub> the 
coefficient of any <em>odd</em> power of <em>x</em> in (6.); but the general form is a little 
different for the coefficients of the <em>odd</em> powers, and not quite so 
convenient.
</p>

<p>

On examining (7.) and (8.), we perceive that, when these formul&aelig; are 
isolated from (6.), whence they are derived, and considered in themselves 
separately and independently, <em>n</em> may be any whole number whatever; 
although when (7.) occurs as <em>one of the</em> D's in (6.), it is obvious that <em>n</em> is 
then not arbitrary, but is always a certain function of the <em>distance of that</em> D 
<em>from the beginning</em>. If that distance be =<em>d</em>, then
</p>

<center>
<img src="figures/notegn1.png" width="394" height="44" alt="" />
</center>

<p>
 
It is with the <em>independent</em> formula (8.) that we have to do. Therefore it 
must be remembered that the conditions for the value of <em>n</em> are now
modified, and that <em>n</em> is a perfectly <em>arbitrary</em> whole
number.  This
circumstance, combined with the fact (which we may 
easily perceive) that whatever <em>n</em> is, every term of (8.) after the (<em>n</em>+1)th is 
=0, and that the (<em>n</em>+1)th term itself is always
<img src="figures/adaeq24.png" align="middle" width="167" height="22"
    alt="=\BB{2n-1}\cdot\frac{1}{1}=\BB{2n-1}" />, enables us
to find the value (either numerical or algebraical) of any <em>n</em>th Number of 
Bernoulli B<sub>2<em>n</em>-1</sub>, <em>in terms of all the preceding ones</em>,
if we but know the 
values of B<sub>1</sub>, B<sub>3</sub>&hellip;B<sub>2<em>n</em>-3</sub>.
We append to this Note a Diagram and Table, 
containing the details of the computation for B<sub>7</sub>
(B<sub>1</sub>, B<sub>3</sub>, B<sub>5</sub> being 
supposed given).
</p>

<p>

On attentively considering (8.), we shall likewise perceive that we may 
derive from it the numerical value of <em>every</em> Number of Bernoulli in 
succession, from the very beginning, <em>ad infinitum</em>, by the following series 
of computations:&mdash;
</p>

<p>

&nbsp;&nbsp;1st Series.&mdash;Let <em>n</em>=1, and calculate (8.) for this value of <em>n</em>. The result is 
B<sub>1</sub>.<br />
&nbsp;&nbsp;2nd Series.&mdash;Let <em>n</em>=2. Calculate (8.) for this value of <em>n</em>, substituting the 
value of B<sub>1</sub> just obtained. The result is B<sub>3</sub>.<br />
&nbsp;&nbsp;3rd Series.&mdash;Let <em>n</em>=3. Calculate (8.) for this value of <em>n</em>, substituting the 
values of B<sub>1</sub>,  B<sub>3</sub> before obtained. The result is  B<sub>5</sub>. And so on, to any 
extent.
</p>

<table border="3" cellpadding="4" style="margin-left: 5px;" align="right">
<tr>
<td><img src="figures/t6clip.png" width="320" height="201" alt="Clip from diagram of computation of the Numbers of Bernoulli" />
</td></tr>
<tr>
<td class="j" width="320">
<font size="-1" face="Helvetica">
The diagram of the computation of the Numbers of Bernoulli is very large
and intricate, and cannot be displayed as an in-line image in this document.
If reduced to fit on a typical computer screen, the text in the diagram is
illegible.  The diagram is available at two different resolutions; the
following links will display the version you select in a separate
browser window (assuming your browser provides this feature), which
will permit you to refer to the diagram, scrolling as necessary, while
reading the following text.  If you have a PostScript printer, you can
<a href="figures/menat6ps.zip">download a ready-to-print</a> PostScript
file (in a ZIPped archive), which prints the diagram on a single page
of paper.
<br />
<br />
View diagram in new browser window:
</font>
<br />
<ul>
<!-- ./textogif -dpi 120 menat6 -->
<li><a href="figures/menat6_1-5k.png" target="_blank">Large image</a> (1560&times;1008 pixels, 69K)</li>
<!-- ./textogif -dpi 150 menat6 -->
<li><a href="figures/menat6_2k.png" target="_blank">Monster image</a> (1949&times;1260 pixels, 100K)</li>
</ul>
</td></tr>
</table>

<p>
The diagram represents the columns of the engine when just prepared for 
computing  B<sub>2<em>n</em>-1</sub> (in the case of <em>n</em>=4);
while the table beneath them 
presents a complete simultaneous view of all the successive changes which 
these columns then severally pass through in order to perform the 
computation. (The reader is referred to <a href="#NoteD">Note D</a>. for explanations 
respecting the nature and notation of such tables.)
</p>

<p>

Six numerical <em>data</em> are in this case necessary for making the requisite 
combinations. These data are 1, 2, <em>n</em>(=4),  B<sub>1</sub>,  B<sub>3</sub>,  B<sub>5</sub>.
Were <em>n</em>=5, the 
additional datum B<sub>7</sub> would be needed. Were <em>n</em>=6,
the datum  B<sub>9</sub> would be 
needed; and so on. Thus the actual <em>number of data</em> needed will always be 
<em>n</em>+2, for <em>n</em>=<em>n</em>;
and out of these <em>n</em>+2 data, <img src="figures/adaeq25.png" align="bottom" width="81" height="18"
    alt="(\overline{n+2}-3)" /> of them are successive 
Numbers of Bernoulli. The reason why the Bernoulli Numbers used as 
data are nevertheless placed on <em>Result</em>-columns in the diagram, is because 
they may properly be supposed to have been previously computed in 
succession by the <em>engine</em> itself; under which circumstances each B will 
appear as a <em>result</em>, previous to being used as a <em>datum</em> for computing the 
succeeding B. Here then is an instance (of the kind alluded to in <a href="#NoteD">Note D</a>.) 
of the same Variables
filling more than one office in turn. It is true that if we consider our 
computation of B<sub>7</sub> as a perfectly isolated calculation, we may conclude  B<sub>1</sub>, 
B<sub>3</sub>,  B<sub>5</sub> to have been arbitrarily placed on the columns; and it would then 
perhaps be more consistent to put them on V<sub>4</sub>, V<sub>5</sub>, V<sub>6</sub> as data and not 
results. But we are not taking this view. On the contrary, we suppose the 
engine to be <em>in the course of</em> computing the Numbers to an indefinite 
extent, from the very beginning; and that we merely single out, by way of 
example, <em>one amongst</em> the successive but distinct series of computations it 
is thus performing. Where the B's are fractional, it must be understood that 
they are computed and appear in the notation of <em>decimal</em> fractions. Indeed 
this is a circumstance that should be noticed with reference to all 
calculations. In any of the examples already given in the translation and in 
the Notes, some of the <em>data</em>, or of the temporary or permanent results, 
might be fractional, quite as probably as whole numbers. But the 
arrangements are so made, that the nature of the processes would be the 
same as for whole numbers.
</p>

<p>

In the above table and diagram we are not considering the <em>signs</em> of any of 
the B's, merely their numerical magnitude. The engine would bring out the 
sign for each of them correctly of course, but we cannot enter on <em>every</em>
additional detail of this kind as we might wish to do. The circles for the 
signs are therefore intentionally left blank in the diagram. 
</p>

<p>

Operation-cards 1, 2, 3, 4, 5, 6 prepare
<img src="figures/adaeq17.png" align="middle" width="77" height="24"
alt="-&frac12;&middot;((2n-1)/(2n+1))" />.
Thus, Card 1
multiplies <em>two</em> into <em>n</em>, and the three
<em>Receiving</em> Variable-cards belonging 
respectively to V<sub>4</sub>, V<sub>5</sub>, V<sub>6</sub>, allow the result 2<em>n</em> to be placed on each of 
these latter columns (this being a case in which a triple receipt of the result 
is needed for subsequent purposes); we see that the upper indices of the 
two Variables used, during Operation 1, remain unaltered.
</p>

<p>

We shall not go through the details of every operation singly, since the 
table and diagram sufficiently indicate them; we shall merely notice some 
few peculiar cases.
</p>

<p>

By Operation 6, a <em>positive</em> quantity is turned
into a <em>negative</em> quantity, by 
simply subtracting the quantity from a column which has only zero upon 
it. (The sign at the top of V<sub>8</sub> would become &minus; during this process.)
</p>

<p>

Operation 7 will be unintelligible, unless it be remembered that if we were 
calculating for <em>n</em> = 1 instead of n = 4, Operation 6 would have completed 
the computation of B<sub>1</sub> itself, in which case the engine instead of 
continuing its processes, would have to put B<sub>1</sub> on V<sub>21</sub>;
and then either to stop altogether, or to begin Operations 1, 2&hellip;7 all over 
again for value of <em>n</em>(=2), in order to enter on the computation of B<sub>3</sub>; 
(having however taken care, previous to this recommencement, to make the 
number on V<sub>3</sub> equal to <em>two</em>, by the addition of
unity to the former <em>n</em>=1 on 
that column). Now Operation 7 must either bring out a result equal to zero 
(if <em>n</em>=1); or a result <em>greater</em> than <em>zero</em>,
as in the present case; and the 
engine follows the one or the other of the two courses just explained, 
contingently on the one or the other result of Operation 7. In order fully to 
perceive the necessity of this <em>experimental</em> operation, it is important to 
keep in mind what was pointed out, that we are not treating a perfectly 
isolated and independent computation, but one out of a series of antecedent 
and prospective computations.
<br clear="right" />
</p>

<p>

Cards 8, 9, 10 produce
<img src="figures/adaeq18.png" align="middle" width="143" height="24"
     alt="-&frac12;&middot;((2n-1)/(2n+1))+B_1(2n/2)" />.
In Operation 9 we see
an example of an upper index which again becomes a value after having 
passed from preceding values to zero. V<sub>11</sub> has
successively been <sup>0</sup>V<sub>11</sub>, 
<sup>1</sup>V<sub>11</sub>, <sup>2</sup>V<sub>11</sub>, <sup>0</sup>V<sub>11</sub>, <sup>3</sup>V<sub>11</sub>; and, from the nature of the office which V<sub>11</sub>
performs in the calculation, its index will continue to go through further 
changes of the same description, which, if examined, will be found to be 
regular and periodic.
</p>

<p>

Card 12 has to perform the same office as Card 7 did in the preceding 
section; since, if <em>n</em> had been =2, the 11th operation would have completed 
the computation of B<sub>3</sub>.
</p>

<p>

Cards 13 to 20 make A<sub>3</sub>. Since A<sub>2<em>n</em>-1</sub>
always consists of 2<em>n</em>-1 factors, 
A<sub>3</sub> has three factors; and it will be seen that
Cards 13, 14, 15, 16 make the 
second of these factors, and then multiply it with the first; and that 17, 18, 
19, 20 make the third factor, and then multiply this with the product of the 
two former factors.
</p>

<p>

Card 23 has the office of Cards 11 and 7 to perform, since if <em>n</em> were =3, the 
21st and 22nd operations would complete the computation of B<sub>5</sub>. As our 
case is B<sub>7</sub>, the computation will continue one more stage; and we must 
now direct attention to the fact, that in order to compute A<sub>7</sub> it is merely 
necessary precisely to repeat the group of Operations 13 to 20; and then, in 
order to complete the computation of B<sub>7</sub>, to repeat Operations 21, 22.
</p>

<p>

It will be perceived that every unit added to <em>n</em> in
B<sub>2<em>n</em>-1</sub>, entails an 
additional repetition of operations (13&hellip;23) for the computation of B<sub>2<em>n</em>-1</sub>. 
Not only are all the <em>operations</em> precisely the same however for every such 
repetition, but they require to be respectively supplied with numbers from 
the very <em>same pairs of columns</em>; with only the one exception of Operation 
21, which will of course need B<sub>5</sub> (from V<sub>23</sub>)
instead of B<sub>3</sub> (from V<sub>22</sub>). 
This identity in the <em>columns</em> which supply
the requisite numbers must not be confounded with identity in the <em>values</em>
those columns have upon them and give out to the mill. Most of those 
values undergo alterations during a performance of the operations 
(13&hellip;23), and consequently the columns present a new set of values for the 
<em>next</em> performance of (13&hellip;23) to work on.
</p>

<p>

At the termination of the <em>repetition</em> of operations (13&hellip;23) in computing 
B<sub>7</sub>, the alterations in the values on the Variables are, that
</p>

<blockquote>
<table>
<tr><td>V<sub>6</sub></td> <td> =</td> <td> 2<em>n</em>-4 instead of 2<em>n</em>-2.</td></tr>
<tr><td>V<sub>7</sub></td> <td> =</td> <td> 6 . . . . . . . . . . . . .  4.</td> </tr>
<tr><td>V<sub>10</sub></td> <td> =</td> <td> 0 . . . . . . . . . . . . .  1.</td> </tr>
<tr><td>V<sub>13</sub></td> <td> =</td> <td> A<sub>0</sub>+A<sub>1</sub>B<sub>1</sub>+A<sub>3</sub>B<sub>3</sub>+A<sub>5</sub>B<sub>5</sub> instead of A<sub>0</sub>+A<sub>1</sub>B<sub>1</sub>+A<sub>3</sub>B<sub>3</sub>.</td></tr>
</table>
</blockquote>

<p>

In this state the only remaining processes are, first, to transfer the
value which is on V<sub>13</sub> to V<sub>24</sub>; and secondly, to
reduce V<sub>6</sub>, V<sub>7</sub>, V<sub>13</sub> to zero, and to
<a name="BKnote21" href="sketch_foot.html#note21">add <em>one</em></a> to V<sub>3</sub>, in order that the engine may be ready to
commence computing B<sub>9</sub>.  Operations 24 and 25 accomplish these
purposes.  It may be thought anomalous that Operation 25 is
represented as leaving the upper index of V<sub>3</sub> still=unity;
but it must be remembered that these indices always begin anew for a
separate calculation, and that Operation 25 places upon V<sub>3</sub>
the <em>first</em> value <em>for the new calculation</em>.
</p>

<p>

It should be remarked, that when the group (13&hellip;23) is <em>repeated</em>, changes 
occur in some of the <em>upper</em> indices during the course of the repetition: for 
example, <sup>3</sup>V<sub>6</sub> would become <sup>4</sup>V<sub>6</sub> and
<sup>5</sup>V<sub>6</sub>.
</p>

<p>

<a name="cycleOfVariables" class="f">We thus see</a> that when <em>n</em>=1, nine Operation-cards are used; that when <em>n</em>=2, 
fourteen Operation-cards are used; and that when <em>n</em>&gt;2, twenty-five 
Operation-cards are used; but that no <em>more</em> are needed, however great <em>n</em>
may be; and not only this, but that these same twenty-five cards suffice for 
the successive computation of all the Numbers from B<sub>1</sub> to B<sub>2<em>n</em>-1</sub>
inclusive. With respect to the number of <em>Variable</em>-cards, it will be 
remembered, from the explanations in previous Notes, that an average of 
three such cards to each <em>operation</em> (not however to each Operation-<em>card</em>) is 
the estimate. According to this, the computation of B<sub>1</sub> will
require twenty-seven Variable-cards; B<sub>3</sub> forty-two such cards;
B<sub>5</sub> seventy-five; and for 
every succeeding B after B<sub>5</sub>, there would be thirty-three additional 
Variable-cards (since each
repetition of the group (13&hellip;23) adds eleven to the number of operations 
required for computing the previous B). But we must now explain, that 
whenever there is a <em>cycle of operations</em>, and if these merely require to be 
supplied with numbers from the <em>same pairs of columns</em>, and likewise each 
operation to place its <em>result</em> on the <em>same</em> column for every repetition of the 
whole group, the process then admits of a <em>cycle of Variable-cards</em> for 
effecting its purposes. There is obviously much more symmetry and 
simplicity in the arrangements, when cases do admit of repeating the 
Variable as well as the Operation-cards. Our present example is of this 
nature. The only exception to a <em>perfect identity</em> in <em>all</em> the processes and 
columns used, for every repetition of Operations (13&hellip;23), is, that 
Operation 21 always requires one of its factors from a new column, and 
Operation 24 always puts its result on a new column. But as these 
variations follow the same law at each repetition (Operation 21 always 
requiring its factor from a column <em>one</em> in advance of that which it used the 
previous time, and Operation 24 always putting its result on the column 
<em>one</em> in advance of that which received the previous result), they are easily 
provided for in arranging the recurring group (or cycle) of Variable-cards.
</p>

<p>

We may here remark, that the average estimate of three Variable-cards 
coming into use to each operation, is not to be taken as an absolutely and 
literally correct amount for all cases and circumstances. Many special 
circumstances, either in the nature of a problem, or in the arrangements of 
the engine under certain contingencies, influence and modify this average 
to a greater or less extent; but it is a very safe and correct <em>general</em> rule to 
go upon. In the preceding case it will give us seventy-five Variable-cards 
as the total number which will be necessary for computing any B after B<sub>3</sub>. 
This is very nearly the precise amount really used, but we cannot here 
enter into the minuti&aelig; of the few particular circumstances which occur in 
this example (as indeed at some one stage or other of probably most 
computations) to modify slightly this number.
</p>

<p>

It will be obvious that the very <em>same</em> seventy-five Variable-cards may be 
repeated for the computation of every succeeding Number, just on the 
same principle as admits of the repetition of the thirty-three
Variable-cards of Operations (13&hellip;23) in the computation of any <em>one</em> Number. Thus 
there will be a <em>cycle of a cycle</em> of Variable-cards.
</p>

<p>

If we now apply the notation for cycles, as explained in <a href="#NoteE">Note E</a>., we may 
express the operations for computing the Numbers of Bernoulli in the 
following manner:&mdash;
</p>

<center>
<!-- ./textogif -dpi 138 notegt1 -->
<img src="figures/notegt1.png" width="632" height="124" alt="" />
</center>
<p>

Again,
</p>

<center>
<img src="figures/notegt2.png" width="564" height="37" alt="" />
</center>

<p>

represents the total operations for computing every number in succession, 
from B<sub>1</sub> to B<sub>2<em>n</em>-1</sub> inclusive.
</p>

<p>

In this formula we see a <em>varying cycle</em> of the <em>first</em> order,
and an ordinary 
cycle of the <em>second</em> order. The latter cycle in this case includes in it the 
varying cycle.
</p>

<p>

On inspecting the ten Working-Variables of the diagram, it will be
perceived, that although the <em>value</em> on any one of them (excepting
V<sub>4</sub> and V<sub>5</sub>) goes through a series of changes, the
<em>office</em> which each performs is in this calculation
<em>fixed</em> and <em>invariable</em>.  Thus V<sub>6</sub> always
prepares the <em>numerators</em> of the factors of any A;
V<sub>7</sub> the <em>denominators</em>.  V<sub>8</sub> always receives the
(2<em>n</em>-3)th factor of A<sub>2<em>n</em>-1</sub>, and
V<sub>9</sub> the (2<em>n</em>-1)th.  V<sub>10</sub> always decides
which of two courses the succeeding processes are to follow, by
feeling for the value of <em>n</em> through means of a subtraction;
and so on; but we shall not enumerate further.  It is desirable in all
calculations so to arrange the processes, that the <em>offices</em>
performed by the Variables may be as uniform and fixed as possible.
</p>

<p>

Supposing that it was desired not only to tabulate B<sub>1</sub>,
B<sub>3</sub>, &amp;c., but A<sub>0</sub>, A<sub>1</sub>, &amp;c.; we have only then
to appoint another series of Variables, V<sub>41</sub>,
V<sub>42</sub>, &amp;c., for receiving these latter results as they are
successively produced upon V<sub>11</sub>.  Or again, we may, instead
of this, or in addition to this second series of results, wish to
tabulate the value of each successive <em>total</em> term of the series (8.),
viz.  A<sub>0</sub>, A<sub>1</sub>B<sub>1</sub>,
A<sub>3</sub>B<sub>3</sub>, &amp;c.  We have then merely to multiply each
B with each corresponding A, as produced, and to place these
successive products on Result-columns appointed for the purpose.
</p>

<p>

The formula (8.) is interesting in another point of view. It is one particular 
case of the general Integral of the following Equation of Mixed Differences:&mdash;
</p>

<center>
<img src="figures/notegn5.png" width="436" height="54"
    alt="\frac{d^2}{dx^2}\left(z_{n+1}x^{2n+2}\right)=(2n+1)(2n+2)z^nx^{2n}" />
</center>

<p>

for certain special suppositions respecting <em>z</em>, <em>x</em> and <em>n</em>.
</p>

<p>

The <em>general</em> integral itself is of the form,
</p>

<center>
<img src="figures/notegn6.png" width="559" height="27"
    alt="z_n=f(n)\cdot x+f_1(n)+f_2(n)\cdot x^{-1}+f_3(n)\cdot x^{-3}+\cdots" />
</center>

<p>

and it is worthy of remark, 
that the engine might (in a manner more or less similar to the preceding) 
calculate the value of this formula upon most <em>other</em> hypotheses for the 
functions in the integral with as much, or (in many cases) with more ease 
than it can formula (8.).
</p>

<p class="r">
A. A. L.
</p>

<center>
<img src="figures/scrule.png" width="448" height="16" alt="----------------------------------------" />
</center>

<p />

<table align="right">
<tr><td align="center">
<form id="feedback" method="post" action="/cgi-bin/FeedbackForm.pl">
<div>
<input type="hidden" name="pagetitle" value="&lt;cite&gt;Sketch of The Analytical Engine&lt;/cite&gt;" />
<input type="hidden" name="backlink" value="Back to &lt;cite&gt;Sketch of The Analytical Engine&lt;/cite&gt;" />
<input type="submit" value=" Send Feedback " />
</div>
</form>
</td></tr>
</table>

<h3><a href="contents.html">Table of Contents</a></h3>
</body>
</html>
